<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<Root><Story><Story><chapter>Characters</chapter> <p1>The term character is used fairly broadly, and refers to the heroes of the Stronghold, leaders, monsters, and even minions and henchmen. All characters are described using aspects, skills, stunts, stress, and consequences. As is typical in games derived from Fate, other parts of the game, like military units, are also described using these same five core elements.</p1> <h1>Heroes</h1> <p1>The term <term>hero</term> is used exclusively to refer to the characters from the Stronghold that the Stronghold players take control of. Such characters may be more anti-hero than hero in play, but it serves to distinguish those characters in the text.</p1> <h2>Aspects</h2> <p1>Heroes have five aspects that are used to describe them. Three of the aspects have particular categories that should be followed, while the other two are flexible. As mentioned in the Fate chapter, aspects are arguably the most important part of the game, and learning how to leverage them is a good skill.</p1> <h3>Core Concept</h3> <p1>The best way to think of the core concept is to imagine how you would concisely describe the character concept to another person. More than any of the other aspects, the core concept should portray the essence of the character. Sample core concepts: <aspect>Commander of the Tarmaeth Legion</aspect>, <aspect>Shadow Council Assassin</aspect>, <aspect>World Weary Animal Tamer</aspect>.</p1> <h3>Trouble</h3> <p1>Every hero has trouble, weaknesses either internal or external that make life difficult. The trouble aspect is a great source for endures or compels. It’s good to make sure the aspect isn’t so narrow that it’s never applicable. Sample troubles: <aspect>Drink to Silence the Screams</aspect>, <aspect>Never Subtle</aspect>, <aspect>In Debt to the Ghall Clan</aspect>.</p1> <h3>Stronghold</h3> <p1>The Stronghold has five aspects, and during the process of character creation, each hero is somehow related to one of those aspects. See the Getting Started chapter for more details. Typically, this aspect signifies what sort of position within the Stronghold the hero holds, but it can also tie the hero to some element of the Stronghold’s history. Frequently the core concept also ties the hero into the Stronghold via rank or position, in which case this aspect can be used to clarify some other part of the hero’s role. Sample Stronghold aspects: <aspect>Medium-sized Fish in a Small Pond</aspect>, <aspect>Echo Lake Farmer</aspect>, <aspect>Warfare Guild Journeyman</aspect>, <aspect>Veteran of the Sunrider Wars</aspect>.</p1> <h2>Relationships</h2> <p1>Heroes have relationships with other heroes as well as with leaders from other factions. When a hero is created, they start with two relationship aspects, one for a positive relationship with another hero, and another for a negative relationship. Positive relationships indicate friendship and comraderie, like <aspect>Aria Was There for Me When No One Else Was</aspect>, <aspect>Gareth is my Mentor</aspect>, <aspect>Ellie has my Back</aspect>. Negative relationships could involve jealousy, irritation, or rough spots from the past. For example, <aspect>Maelgwn is Terribly Naive</aspect>, <aspect>Ollie Broke My Heart</aspect>, <aspect>Tyra is Self-centered</aspect>. Negative relationships are good sources for endure actions and compels.</p1> <p1>It is possible to get more relationships than the starting two via stunts. Sometimes during the mission it’s desirable to use Create an Advantage to create aspects that are relationships with different characters. These relationships useful during the game, but aren’t elevated to the level of relationship aspects that are added to the character sheet, so they tend to be more superficial or temporary.</p1> <h3>Free Invokes</h3> <p1>At the start of every mission, each relationship aspect gets refreshed with one free invoke.</p1> <h2>Skills</h2> <p1>Skills are broad areas of expertise and ability that characters possess. Heroes start with one Great (+4) skill, two Good (+3) skills, three Fair (+2) skills, and four Average (+1) skills. The rest of the skills start at Mediocre (+0). Over the course of the campaign, skills can improve and increase in rank. The only restriction is that every skill above the Mediocre rank must have at least one skill below it in rank.</p1> <h2>Stunts</h2> <p1>Stunts are special abilities and improvements tied to skills. Each hero starts with one stunt for their Great (+4) skill. Each time a skill advances to the rank of Great (+4) or above, the hero may take one stunt for that skill. Stunts are listed under each skill description in the <chapref>Skills and Stunts</chapref> chapter.</p1> <h2>Stress and Consequences</h2> <p1>Stress and Consequences are a way to handle duress, hardships, and even injuries as well as functioning as a pacing mechanism. Heroes start with a physical stress track of length two as well as a mental stress track of length two. A Physique skill above Mediocre (+0) gives the hero extra physical stress boxes and a possible bonus consequences, and a Will skill above Mediocre (+0) gives the hero extra mental stress boxes and a possible bonus consequence. See the <chapref>Skills and Stunts</chapref> chapter for the specifics.</p1> <p1>Heroes also start with a minor (-2), major (-4), and severe (-6) consequence. All stress as well as any minor consequences taken are removed at the end of each mission, while major and severe consequences take longer to remove. The major consequence takes a season of downtime, while the severe consequence takes four seasons of downtime. Consequences function as aspects when they’re taken, and get a free invoke. Consequences can be fairly broad, representing physical damage (<aspect>Sprained Ankle</aspect>), mental anguish (<aspect>Night Terrors</aspect>), or even obligations (<aspect>Debt to Heinrich</aspect>) and passions (<aspect>Infatuated with Ellis</aspect>).</p1> <p1>Heroes can go on missions with consequences, although it’s riskier. Of course, going on a mission doesn’t count as down time for making progress to remove major and severe consequences.</p1> <h2>Concessions</h2> <p1>As described in the Taking Damage section of the <chapref>Fate</chapref> chapter, if a character must take stress but has no more stress boxes or consequences to mitigate the stress, they are taken out. A character that is taken out is at the mercy of the player who took them out to determine their fate. Usually, the character is no longer available for the campaign.</p1> <p1>Prior to being taken out, a player may propose a concession. This is a condition to avoid being taken out that is accepted by the Autarch player. Concessions must be proposed before any dice are rolled for actions. Concessions might involve taking consequences or agreeing to different conditions for the current mission, such as partial success.</p1> <h1>Leaders</h1> <p1>Other important and possibly recurring characters in the campaign are faction <term>leaders</term>, important characters related to the other factions in the game, as well as <term>bosses</term>, humans and other creatures that typically function as adversaries during missions. Leaders and bosses are built almost identically to heroes, with the key difference coming from how skills and stunts are chosen.</p1> <h2>Aspects</h2> <p1>Named characters typically have four aspects, which don’t have to be categorized as the hero aspects do.</p1> <h2>Rank</h2> <p1>Named characters are built around a rank, which gives an indicator of their overall ability and highest skill rank. A named character’s rank is described using the fate ladder just as skills are.</p1> <p1>Instead of a skill pyramid, named characters begin with two skills at every level above Mediocre (+0) up to their rank. The rest of their skills are Mediocre (+0). Most leaders have a Superb (+5) rank, while boss monsters generally have a rank based on the difficulty of the mission. Unlike heroes, named characters never improve their skills over the course of the campaign.</p1> <h2>Stunts</h2> <p1>Named characters get one stunt if they are rank Great (+4) or below and one additional stunt for each rank above Great (+4). Most leaders start with two stunts.</p1> <h2>Stress and Consequences</h2> <p1>Stress tracks and starting consequences are calculated for named characters as they are for heroes. Any stress or consequences suffered by named leaders are recovered at the end of the season.</p1> <h2>Concessions</h2> <p1>The Autarch player can offer concessions for named characters as the Stronghold players do for heroes in order to avoid being taken out.</p1> <h1>Lieutenants</h1> <p1>Lieutenants are minor characters that </p1> <h1>Minions</h1> <p1>Lieutenants are minor characters that </p1> <h1>Units</h1> <p1>TBD</p1> <h2>Skills</h2> <p1>TBD</p1> <h2>Stress</h2> <p1>TBD</p1> <h2>Consequences</h2> <p1>TBD</p1> <h1>Henchmen</h1> <p1>TBD</p1> <h2>Actions</h2> <p1>TBD</p1> <h2>Aspect Burning</h2> <p1>TBD</p1></Story></Story></Root>
