<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<Root><Story><chapter>Diplomacy</chapter> <p1>The Diplomacy conflict is used for social situations where two parties attempt to come to an agreement. Frequently, this is part of a Trade mission, where the Stronghold desires to set up a trade agreement with another faction. However, Diplomacy can also feature in Threats as well as Exploration.</p1>   <p1>During Diplomacy, the heroes attempt to gain the support of influential leaders of the opposing side in order to complete a deal. Each leader has an <term>influence</term> value that measures how important their support is. The heroes try to gain the support of as many leaders as possible. At the end of Diplomacy, the total support gained determines how successful the mission is. For Trade missions, the amount of support needed varies based on the terms of the trade agreement. If the deal is very good for the Stronghold and not so good for the faction, a high amount of support from the faction leaders is necessary for the deal to be successful.</p1>  <p1>Before Diplomacy is started, a <term>Leader Support Track</term> and a <term>Total Support Track</term> should be copied from the back of the book. These sheets track the total amount of support as well as how close each leader is to lending their support.</p1> <h1>Challenges</h1> <p1>For Trade missions, there are sample challenges listed in the chapter for the target faction. The <chapref>Threats</chapref> chapter and the <chapref>Regions</chapref> chapter also have sample challenges for Threat and Exploration missions, respectively.</p1> <p1>Challenges during Diplomacy missions can focus on the relationships of the leaders toward the Stronghold. What sort of cultural differences are there? How do the heroes go about negotiating the customs of the people? Good challenges here can also focus on exposing in-fighting between different factions, thus forcing the heroes to choose sides.</p1> <h1>Opposition</h1> <p1>Each mission lists the leaders the Stronghold players will negotiate with. For Trade missions, these are leaders from the faction, as described in the faction chapters. The leaders are influential characters whose opinions matter the most toward getting a deal done. Choose one leader for each hero on the mission.</p1> <p1>If there aren’t enough leaders for some reason, possibly due to assassination, create a number of lieutenants until the number of leaders and lieutenants equals the number of heroes. Lieutenants will have a rank equal to the difficulty of the mission. Good skills for lieutenants are Will, Society, Rapport, Empathy, and Deceive. Each faction chapter has a list of typical names for people from that faction, which make a good source of inspiriation for naming lieutenants.</p1> <h2>Influence</h2> <p1>The total influence of all the opposition should equal 16. Divide the 16 points of influence amongst all the leaders and lieutenants in the opposition. Each opposing character should have at least one influence, and no more influence than twice either their Society or Leadership skill ranks.</p1> <h1>Setup</h1> <p1>Both the Leader Support Tracker and Total Support Tracker need to be set up before playing through the Diplomacy conflict. In addition, for Trade missions, the value of the trade agreement needs to be calculated.</p1> <h2>Trade Value</h2> <p1>This step only needs to be done for Trade missions. Every trade agreement has a value from -2 (a good deal for the opposing faction) up to +2 (a good deal for the Stronghold). This value is determined by using the <term>trade chart</term> for the faction in question. This can be found in the faction chapters, as well as in summary form at the back of the book. The trade charts list both what the faction wants as well as what’s available for them to give. Each faction has a different trade chart, with unique trade offers based on the particular faction.</p1> <p1>Before a Trade mission begins, an initial offer is constructed by the spotlight player. This is done by looking at the listing of available goods and services. Each of these goods and services has a rating from one to five. The spotlight player chooses one entry for that is desired by the Stronghold. The chosen entry will be received by the Stronghold each season.</p1> <p1>There is a restriction on what the Stronghold may ask for. The cost of the entry must be less than or equal to the faction’s disposition score. Some measure of goodwill must be present before the costlier items are available!</p1> <example>The players are in a Trade mission with Burgan Vale, which has the goods and services listed on the following chart. It is currently the Spring and Burgan Vale’s disposition is 4. Jenn, the spotlight player, decides that getting 2 Arcane BP in a trade agreement would be very useful in the Stronghold’s effort to build a mage tower. Thus, the cost of what the Stronghold is asking for is 4. The option to get 5 mana a season isn’t available because disposition isn’t high enough.</example> <statblock><Table xmlns:aid="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/4.0/" aid:table="table" aid:trows="9" aid:tcols="2"><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="2"><b>Burgan Vale Available Goods and Services</b></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">Value</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">Good / Service</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5"><b>1</b></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">1 Mana</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5"><b>2</b></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">2 Mana</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5"></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">1 Arcane BP</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5"><b>3</b></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">3 Mana</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5"><b>4</b></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">4 Mana</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5"></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">2 Arcane BP</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5"><b>5</b></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">5 Mana</Cell></Table></statblock> <p1>After determining what the Stronghold wants, choose an entry on the trade chart desired by the faction. There is an additional restriction in calculating what the Stronghold will offer. The value of the goods and services that the Stronghold gives to the faction must be within 2 of the value of the goods and services received by the Stronghold. So, if the Stronghold wants something of value 4, they must give something of at least value 2 and no more than value 6.</p1> <p1>To find the value of the trade agreement, subtract the value of what the Stronghold gives from what the Stronghold receives. This yields a trade agreement value from -2 (very good deal for the faction) to +2 (very good deal for the Stronghold).</p1> <example>Continuing on from the above example, the Stronghold players decide to give Burgan Vale 6 ore each season. The value of 6 ore is 3. So, the value of the trade agreement is 4 (2 Arcane BP) - 3 (6 ore) = +1. This isn’t a great deal for Burgan Vale, so the Stronghold players are going to need lots of support to make this happen!</example> <statblock><Table xmlns:aid="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/4.0/" aid:table="table" aid:trows="7" aid:tcols="2"><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="2"><b>Burgan Vale Desired Goods and Services</b></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">Value</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">Good / Service</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5"><b>1</b></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">2 Ore</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5"><b>2</b></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">4 Ore</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5"><b>3</b></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">6 Ore</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5"><b>4</b></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">8 Ore</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5"><b>5</b></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">10 Ore</Cell></Table></statblock> <h2>Total Support Track</h2> <p1>If playing a Trade mission, fill in the top part of the Total Support Track with the trade agreement specifics, including the trade value. Place a token of some kind on the 0 space of the total support track, and another token on the current exchange indicator in the 4 space. The Diplomacy conflict lasts for a total of 4 exchanges. The total support track records the total influence from all the opposition leaders the Stronghold has the support of.</p1> <p1>For Trade missions, there are trade value numbers above the total support track (from -2 to +2) that show the total influence support needed for success. For other types of missions, the total support needed for success is found in the mission description. At the end of the Diplomacy conflict, the total support counter must be at or above this amount to succeed.</p1> <h2>Leader Support Track</h2> <p1>The leader support tracks should be filled out with the name, influence, and Society skill of each leader or lieutenant opposing the Stronghold. A counter for each leader should be placed on the space equal to their Will skill. The higher their Will, the more difficult it is to gain their support. Using miniatures for these tracks can be a particularly visual way to represent how close each leader is to supporting the offer. There is an additional space for using a token of some sort to remember when each leader has taken their turn during the exchange. If a leader moves down the track to the <term>supportive</term> space, they lend their influence to the total support gained so far by the Stronghold and no longer take any actions during the Diplomacy conflict.</p1> <h2>Exchange</h2> <p1>Turns are taken in order of the Society skill, with the highest character going first, working down. Use Leadership to break ties. If still tied, the Stronghold player may choose the order. Each character takes one action on their turn before a new exchange begins. After each exchange, lower the exchange tracker on the total support tracking sheet. After four exchanges, the Diplomacy conflict is over.</p1> <p1>Characters may delay their action until later in the exchange, potentially forcing characters with lower Society skills to go first.</p1> <h1>Actions</h1> <p1>When a character takes a turn, they choose one of the actions from the list below. Some actions are only available to heroes while some are only available to the opposition leaders. Only heroes may take the Gain Support, Address Issue, and Change Offer actions. Only leaders may take the Raise Issue action.</p1> <h2>Create an Advantage</h2> <p1>Any player may declare either a phase aspect during their turn, following the normal rules for Create an Advantage in the <chapref>Fate</chapref> chapter. Remember that aspects which directly target specfic characters should be actively opposed, rather than using the passive difficulty.</p1> <h3>Raise Issue</h3> <p1>A special use of Create an Advantage available to the opposition is to raise concerns about the heroes, the Stronghold, or the deal proposed. This roll is always opposed by one of the heroes, using a particularly relevant skill. The spotlight player may choose who opposes the roll.</p1> <p1>If the action is successful, not only is an aspect created with one or two free invokes, but the total support track is decreased by 2 until this issue is addressed. If the action fails, the Stronghold players may create a boost as normal for the Create an Advantage action.</p1> <p1>Furthermore, if this is a Trade mission, the value of the trade agreement modifies this roll. For example, if the trade value is -2 (a really good deal for the faction), the leader subtracts 2 from the roll to Raise an Issue. It’s harder to raise issues when you’re looking at a really good deal!</p1> <example>The Stronghold of Aben’s Hollow is on a Trade mission with Burgan Vale. Marellus, a leader from Burgan Vale, is skeptical of dealing with Aben’s Hollow. “Will they honor the land? Do they respect the Veil as we do?” The Autarch player decides Leadership is the best skill to use for this sort of argument. The spotlight player for Aben’s Hollow decides Fuscus, their key diplomat, will oppose the roll with Channeling, using the knowledge of magic to reassure the leadership Burgan Vale. “We have always valued the natural energies of the land. I can see the magic all around this place, I even see the colors of Blue Rock swirling about you right now. Yes, it’s subtle, but I detect it.”</example> <example>The Autarch player makes an opposed roll against the Stronghold player controlling Fuscus, and succeeds by 1. This is enough to create an aspect with one free invoke, as well as lower the total support track by two. “I’m sorry, but many people have such vision - will you honor the land or will you exploit it?” The Autarch player writes <aspect><fate>1</fate> Concerned That Aben’s Hollow Won’t Protect The Land</aspect> on a note card.</example> <h2>Overcome</h2> <p1>In Diplomacy, the Overcome action can be used to remove phase aspects as normal, but it is more commonly used in one of the following ways.</p1> <h3>Gain Support</h3> <p1>Gaining support is the most common action taken by the heroes in Diplomacy. To gain support, one of the leaders or lieutenants of the opposition is chosen, and the hero attempts to persuade them that the deal is worthwhile. Note that tactics like blackmail and physical intimidation aren’t as appropriate here. Those would fall under the Attack action. Instead, gaining support is an attempt to build bridges and point out the merits of a longer term alliance, although lies of omission and more general misleading is fine.</p1> <p1>The Stronghold player chooses the skill which best matches the nature of the argument used. The Autarch player chooses a skill best suited to resist or point out problems with the argument. An opposed roll is used to determine whether the Stronghold player is successful or not.</p1> <p1>If successful, the faction leader is moved one step toward supportive on the faction leader support track for each positive shift. If the faction leader drops below zero on the leader support track, they are now agreeable to the offer and lend support.</p1> <p1>Once a leader becomes supportive, they can never become unsupportive. They no longer take any actions on their turn. When they become supportive, their influence score is added to the total support track.</p1> <h3>Address Issue</h3> <p1>This works the same as the general Overcome action described in the Fate chapter, but targets an issue raised during Diplomacy. If successful, the issue is removed, and the total support track is increased by 2 to offset the decrease that occurred when the issue was added. This action is typically opposed by the leader that raised the issue, although it may be opposed by anyone on the opposition.</p1> <h2>Attack</h2> <p1>Instead of taking the high ground and arguing the merits of the deal, a character may decide to attack another’s mental stress. As is true for all the conflicts, this is a broad use of the term Attack. In Diplomacy, it never means physical violence, but rather blackmail, intimidation, lies, or even seduction. Note that relationship aspects which suggest a positive relationship will prevent this (remember, aspects are always true and are first and foremost facts about the world). Friends don’t use such underhanded tactics against other friends! A good use of Create an Advantage is to create such aspects to prevent being attacked by particularly devious characters.</p1> <p1>The skills commonly used for attacking and those which oppose them are:</p1> <ul><l1>Intimidation vs. Will</l1> <l1>Deceive vs. Empathy</l1> <l1>Leadership vs. Leadership</l1></ul> <p1>If a character is taken out, they no longer take actions for the rest of the Diplomacy conflict. If the character is a leader, they will lend their support to the deal, succumbing to the underhanded tactics. All the normal results for being taken out as described in the <chapref>Fate</chapref> chapter also apply.</p1> <h2>Defend</h2> <p1>This action works as described in the Fate chapter. Defense typically uses Empathy to sniff out lies, Will to resist blackmail and seduction, and Leadership to resist claims of authority and power.</p1> <h2>Change Offer</h2> <p1>This action is only available for Trade missions. If Diplomacy isn’t going well, and time is running out, changing the offer is a good way to at least get something instead of wasting a whole season in fruitless diplomacy. To change the offer, the current player constructs a new trade agreement by following the steps used to determine the trade offer in the setup.</p1> <p1>The new trade value must be equal to or less than the old trade value. That is, the deal must favor the faction at least as much as the old one does, so this is usually done when time is running out and offering a better deal to the faction will make it possible to gain the necessary support.</p1> <h1>Resolution</h1> <p1>After each exchange, the total support marker is checked to see if it is at or above the total support level needed for the mission. If it is, Diplomacy is over, and the Stronghold is successful.</p1> <p1>If enough support hasn’t been gained, then the exchange indicator on the total support track is checked. When it drops down to 0, Diplomacy is over and no deal is reached. The Stronghold suffers the effects of failure described for the mission.</p1></Story></Root>
