<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<!DOCTYPE Root SYSTEM "BookChapter.dtd">
<Root>
    <Story>
        <chapter>Fate</chapter>
        <p1>Wrath of the Autarch is a game built on the Fate engine, as described in Fate Core, released by Evil Hat Productions. Furthermore, WotA was influenced by other Fate games released prior to Fate Core, in particular, the science fiction RPG Diaspora. There are many other great Fate RPGs as well, such as Spirit of the Century, The Dresden Files, and Legends of Anglerre.</p1> 
        <p1>If you’re completely unfamiliar with Fate, reading this chapter is fairly important, and grabbing a copy of Fate Core is also very helpful. Alternatively, if you’re old hat at Fate, particularly the brand described in Fate Core, this chapter may be skimmed. Although, pay particularly close attention to the Create an Advantage action, which has a few twists to deal with the creation of permanent aspects.</p1> 
        <h2>Using Dice</h2> 
        <p1>There are certain commonalities that appear in most FATE games, and WotA is no exception. The first is the use of Fudge (or Fate) dice. These are dice with the symbol ‘+’ on two faces, the symbol ‘-’ on two faces, and blanks on the other faces. In WotA, as in most Fate games, four of these dice are rolled whenever there is a conflict that is in doubt, and the dice are summed (treat ‘+’ as ‘+1’ and ‘-‘ as ‘-1’), yielding a result between -4 and +4. This roll is notated in these rules as 4dF. The results form a bell curve, with the most likely result being zero.</p1> 
        <p1>Alternatively, two six sided dice may be rolled, and one dice result may be subtracted from the other. This yields a result between -5 and +5. It is also much more chaotic than the 4dF method. Generally, chaos only serves to make it more difficult for the players, but it is an option if you like a great range of results.</p1> 
        <h3>Dice Rolls</h3> 
        <p1>Almost all rolls in WotA involve a skill, an area of expertise pertaining to a character. These skill rolls may apply to passive opposition, like climbing a wall, or active opposition, which is always another character. All skills are rated on what is known as ‘The Ladder’, a series of adjectives that can be used to describe the rank of the skill (how high it is). Whether to use numbers or adjectives is largely a matter of preference. </p1> 
        <ul>•	+8 Legendary •	+7 Epic •	+6 Fantastic •	+5 Superb •	+4 Great •	+3 Good •	+2 Fair •	+1 Average •	0 Mediocre •	-1 Poor •	-2 Terrible</ul> 
        <p1>A roll against passive opposition is notated in these rules as 4dF + skill + modifiers vs. target number. In this case, if the sum of 4dF plus the skill and any modifiers equals or exceeds the target number, the roll is successful.</p1> 
        <p1>An active opposition roll involves two characters, each choosing an appropriate skill to roll. The character opposing the roll is usually referred to as the opposition or the defender.The roll is notated by 4dF + skill + modifiers vs. 4dF + skill + modifiers, where the latter is the defender’s roll. If the roll equals or exceeds the defender’s roll, it is successful. </p1> 
        <p1>If the roll is successful, each point beyond the target number (for a fixed roll) or defender’s roll (for an opposed roll) is referred to as a shift. The number of shifts is frequently important to track. For instance, shifts could reflect damage in combat (each point the attacker achieves above the defender’s roll is tracked as physical stress which could kill the defender). If the roll is equal to the target number of defender’s roll, there are no shifts, but the roll itself is considered a success and may trigger certain effects. Gaining three shifts means success with style, and generally confers extra benefits. </p1> 
        <h2>Aspects</h2> 
        <p1>Aspects are short descriptive words and phrases which add flavor to the narrative, as well as give mechanical advantages and disadvantages to die rolls. Aspects are the most important part of the game, and can be attached to almost anything: characters, factions, regions, relationships, terrain, and more.</p1> 
        <p1>Character aspects relate to individuals, frequently heroes, and include examples like Fiery Temper or Stubborn Temperament. Aspects which describe a faction might be Magocracy or Uneducated Population. Aspects may also relate to a region such as Flush with Game or they may even describe very transient effects, such as Ambush Perch or Slippery Floor.</p1> 
        <p1>See the Fate Core rules for a wealth of information about how to create and use aspects effectively.</p1>   
        <h2>Fate Points</h2> 
        <p1>The FATE system uses a currency called fate points to take advantage of aspects during play. Most Fate players use poker chips to track fate points, but any sort of token may be used. Each character receives a number of fate points at the start of each mission (this number is almost always three, although it could be modified by other effects).  </p1>
        <p1>The main reason fate points are spent is to invoke aspects. Invoking an aspect gives the character a mechanical advantage, as long as the player can narrate how the aspect in question will help their skill roll. Note, any beneficial aspect may be invoked, not just one on your character sheet. Another common reason to spend fate points is to use certain powerful stunts that a character has. The results are described in the description of the stunt.</p1> 
        <p1>One of the ways fate points are received is via a compel, which occurs when an aspect places the hero into a difficult position. Compels are a way for the players to gain fate points. Compels are always pulled from the general supply of fate points, they don’t come from a personal pool. Frequently, the GM initiates compels, although this doesn’t have to be the case. </p1> 
        <p1>The GM starts each mini-game with some fate points, and can also gain fate points if the players take a particularly long time to finish the narrative phase. This supply of fate points is used by the GM so that adversaries in the mini-game may invoke aspects to thwart the players. This is described in more detail in the Missions chapter.</p1> 
        <h3>Phases and Fate Points</h3> 
        <p1>The option to invoke aspects works basically the same regardless of whether the group is playing through the narrative phase or the tactical mini-game. However, there are additional ways to spend fate points during the mini-games, mostly available to the GM in order to trigger certain effects or actions. See the mini-games chapters (Infiltration, Diplomacy, Skirmish, and Warfare) for more details.</p1> 
        <p1>Compels only occur in the narrative phase – the tactical mini-games don’t use compels.</p1> 
        <h3>Invoking an Aspect</h3> 
       <p1>Invoking an aspect is a way to use an aspect for a mechanical benefit. The player invoking the aspect narrates how it will help in the situation represented by the dice roll. If an aspect is invoked, there are two different mechanical benefits that can be taken advantage of, after any fixed or opposed skill roll. Each aspect invoked costs one fate point.</p1> 
        <ul>•	Reroll all of the dice •	Add +2 to the result</ul> 
        <p1>There is a restriction on invoking aspects: on any given roll, any single aspect may only be invoked once (although see below about free invokes). </p1>

        <h3>Compelling an Aspect</h3> 

        <p1>Compelling an aspect makes the situation more difficult for the character being compelled. As mentioned, this mostly occurs during the narrative phase. There are a number of other differences between compels and invokes as well. Compels may be initiated by any player at the table, while invoking aspects is done only by the player who just finished the dice roll. Furthermore, where invokes tend to have concrete mechanical benefits on dice rolls, compels tend to constrain the ongoing story in new ways or color the flavor of narration.</p1> 

        <p1>Also unlike invokes, a player that is compelled may buy off the compel by spending one of their fate points. This usually occurs when they don’t want to incur whatever negative situation will result from the compel, and are willing to spend a fate point to ignore it. Summary of Invokes and Compels</p1> 

        <p1>In summary, aspects are invoked after the dice are rolled, and provide a mechanical benefit. Compels might occur before or after the dice or rolled, and mainly affect the story rather than any particular roll. The interplay between using aspects and moving fate points around the table is one of the most important parts of the game.</p1> 

        <ul>Spend Fate Points •	Invoke an aspect •	Power certain stunts •	(GM) Certain mini-game actions Receive Fate Points •	Compels •	(GM) If the players take too long in the narrative phase •	(GM) Start of mini-game</ul>   

        <h3>Creating Aspects</h3> 

        <p1>Frequently during play, the players will want to make new aspects. Bringing new aspects into play is referred to as Creating an Advantage. Aspects are made by making a skill check with a skill related to the desired aspect. Permanent, mission, and phase aspects may be created.</p1> 

        <p1>Permanent aspects are, as their name implies, permanent. Even more than their status as permanent, they tend to be more significant than other aspects, as they are a long lasting fact about the world. Permanent aspects must relate to a region, faction, or relationship with some other character in the game.</p1> 

        <p1>The aspect is written on the Stronghold Sheet in the regions section, the Factions Sheet under the appropriate faction, or on the Character Sheet in the relationships section. </p1> 

        <p1>Note that modifying the Stronghold’s aspects or one of the heroes’ aspects is not covered under the Creating an Advantage rules. This action creates new aspects, and the heroes and the Stronghold start the campaign with their full contingent of aspects.</p1> 

        <p1>Example: Terri is playing the character Gwynnet, who has a Nature skill of 5. Traveling through the Dusk’s Ayrie, she has the idea of creating a new permanent aspect related to nature. “I’m thinking that Gwynnet discovers some sort of healing plants in the area using her Nature skill.” The GM agrees with the declaration, and notes the difficulty is 5 to create a permanent aspect. Terri rolls 4dF, getting a +2, for a total of 7. She writes down Restorative Red Berries of Gumja Shrubs under the Dusk’s Ayrie region of the Stronghold sheet. Besides adding to the story, these berries may be invoked sometime later on down the road – perhaps when someone is injured. </p1> 

        <p1>The mission aspects are in play for the duration of a mission. As such, they are frequently created during the narrative phase to set up advantages during the tactical mini-game. </p1> 

        <p1>Example: Using a character’s Investigation skill to add the aspect No Honor among Thieves to describe a group of bandits in the area who are stealing ore. Both permanent and mission aspects are generally only created during the narrative phase. Because the tactical mini-games are the final phase of the mission, mission aspects and phase aspects are equivalent, so it doesn’t make much sense to construct mission aspects. The permanent aspects, on the other hand, usually reflect some measure of research and time investment that usually isn’t possible during the focused time restrictions of tactical mini-games. More detail is given in the Missions chapter and the different mini-game chapters.</p1> 

        <p1>Phase aspects are fairly similar to mission aspects, although they are generally only useful for a narrower range of time. For instance, a player could use Science to construct a Makeshift Bridge when trying to cross a gorge. Even though a bridge is in many ways permanent, by making it a phase aspect, it is understood that the bridge will be used only during the narrative phase, maybe to help cross a rampaging river, and won’t make another appearance later. Changing the tactical landscape of a fight during a Skirmish, by placing a Brush Fire aspect on an area of ground, might also be a phase aspect. </p1>

        <p1>Boosts are one use aspects. The duration of a boost may be any length of time (boosts can be permanent, mission, or phase), but once it is used, the aspect goes away. Boosts are usually created as a side effect of various stunts or certain rolls.</p1> 

        <h3>Free Invokes</h3> 

        <p1>Whenever a new aspect is created through the Create an Advantage action, the first time it is invoked, the player invoking or compelling it does not have to spend a fate point. The player who created the aspect has the final say in what players are allowed this free invoke, also subject to how the aspect fits within the current situation.</p1> 

        <p1>Furthermore, free invokes may be combined with the spending of a fate point, thus breaking the rule that an aspect may be invoked at most once on any given roll. Even further, sometimes an aspect will have more than one free invoke, allowing it to be invoked more than once for free.</p1> 

        <p1>Thus, an aspect with two free invokes could be used to add +6 to a roll (if both free invokes are used and additionally a fate point is spent).</p1> 

        <p1>This rule highlights why the creation of aspects is so handy. Even if characters are having trouble contributing directly to a situation through the use of skills, they may use other skills to create aspects which may be free invoked by another player to succeed.</p1> 

        <h3>Tracking Aspects</h3> 

        <p1>Any system can be used to track free invokes and boosts. One system that works fairly well is to draw open square boxes next to free invokes, which are then filled in if the aspect is invoked for free. Boosts can then be tracked by open circles, and the entire aspect is removed when it is used.</p1> 

        <h2>Working with the GM</h2> 

        <p1>Sometimes, in the construction of an aspect, the player has an idea which is very similar to an aspect that a character controlled by the GM already has. In this case, the GM may simply reveal the aspect, and use it instead of the aspect proposed by the player. Although the aspect isn’t new in relation to the game world, it is new in relation to the character, and bringing it out into the open increases its importance and gives a narrative element mechanical weight.</p1> 

        <p1>Alternatively, a player may only have a general idea about an aspect, but is having trouble coming up with anything. It’s fine to ask the GM if using a skill would result in an aspect that might be useful.</p1> 

        <p1>In practice, creating new aspects initiates a conversation with the GM. Certain ideas the player has may directly contradict facts about the game world, and as such should be discussed more until there is good consensus.  </p1>

        <p1>As a general rule of thumb, the GM should error on the side of allowing the declaration of new aspects. It helps invest the players into the story, and helps enrich the narrative.</p1> 

        <h3>Aspects as Facts about the World</h3> 

        <p1>More so than many role-playing games, RPGs using the FATE system are greatly aided by the participation of the players in the flowing narrative. Aspects are one of primary ways this can happen. While they do give mechanical hooks into narrative traits, they are also facts about the world. They help to define people, places, and things.</p1> 

        <p1>Since WotA has such a tight restriction on scenes, creating these facts allows the players to set up actions in the future. For instance, a player could use their character’s Society skill to declare that a tribe of kobolds live nearby. Later, another character could use the Thieves Tools stunt to steal from them.</p1> 

        <h3>The Art of Describing Aspects</h3> 

        <p1>Making aspects can take some practice. In particular, aspects for the characters and Stronghold are ideally able to be interpreted positively and negatively. For instance, Impetuous could allow a character to act quickly when danger is discovered, but it could also be compelled to get the character into trouble.</p1> 

        <p1>Without aspects which are easy to compel, it becomes very difficult to gain fate points. Similarly, if an aspect is difficult to invoke, it won’t provide as much mechanical benefit. See the Fate Core book for tons of guidance on the subject.</p1> 

        <p1>Also, because aspects help add flavor to the world, giving them color can add to the story. For instance, a character could be a Swordmaster or they could be a Disciple of the Nine Blade Whirlwind Technique. Sure, they probably both apply in similar situations, but the latter is far more suggestive of details and story hooks to uncover later.Granted, every aspect doesn’t have to be that way, it’s hard to add much color to a Brush Fire in an area, and frequently a character is just Flanked or Ambushed.  </p1> 

        <h2>Core Actions</h2> 

        <p1>There are three types of actions taken by both the players and the GM which are used throughout these rules (pulled from Fate Core). They are Create an Advantage, Overcome Obstacle, and Attack. These actions are sometimes tweaked a little depending on whether they’re taken during the narrative phase or during one of the mini-games, but for the most part they work as described here.  </p1>

        <p1>Each of the core actions involves a skill check – either against passive or active opposition. The Attack action is almost always against active opposition (either a hero is attacking a character the GM controls, or vice versa). Also, the Attack action is not available in the narrative phase. It is only part of the mini-games. C Create an Advantage (Create or Refresh an Aspect) This action was discussed in the earlier section, but the actual mechanics involved are covered here. Creating an advantage action allows a player to create aspects during their turn.</p1> 
        <p1>If the aspect is created during the narrative phase or if it involves passive opposition, the difficulty for the skill check is based on how long the aspect will remain in play. The longer, and thus more impactful the aspect is, the more difficult it is to create.</p1> 
        <ul>Aspect Type	Target Permanent	5 Mission	4 Phase	3</ul> 
        <p1>During the mini-games, creating an aspect frequently involves active opposition. In this case, the creation of the aspect is opposed by a relevant skill the opponent possesses. Aspects created in such a manner are considered permanent until the target uses an Overcome Obstacle action to remove them, or the fiction changes in such a way that they become irrelevant.</p1> 
        <p1>Example: Trying to create the Flanked aspect on the ogre targets the beast, so it merits an opposed Athletics check, or some other relevant skill, to create. The duration of the aspect reflects the scope in which it is useful, not the fact that it may or may not be transient. For instance, a player could attempt to create the phase aspect Makeshift Raft using Science. While the raft is not a transient effect, the point of making it a phase aspect is that it will no longer be featured after the narrative phase is over.</p1> 
        <p1>It is easiest to write phase and mission aspects on note cards, while permanent aspects should be written on the Stronghold sheet (if they apply to a region the characters are in), the Factions sheet (if they apply to another faction), or the Character sheet (if they apply to relationships with other characters in the game). Note that the heroes’ aspects and the Stronghold’s aspects are not modified this way – they are adjusted outside the scope of the mission.</p1> 
        <p1>The results depend on the outcome of a 4dF + skill roll, compared to the opposition.</p1> 
        <ul>•	Failure. If a player fails the roll, either no aspect is created, or the GM can create an aspect related to the desired aspect, which may not entirely be what the player had in mind. The aspect may not be invoked for free. •	Tie. In the case of a tie, the player creates a boost. The scope of the boost will be the same (so a mission boost will last the whole mission), but as usual, it may only be invoked once, for free, and then it is removed from play. •	Success. Create an aspect of the appropriate scope which may be invoked once for free. •	Succeed with Style. In this case, the aspect is created as usual, but it may be invoked twice for free, rather than once. Draw two free invokes on the aspect. Setting up permanent aspects during a somewhat easier mission can be very useful later on during more difficult missions. That Contact within the Thieves Guild that was found during a Trade mission to Lily Manor could later be invoked once for free during a difficult Espionage mission to the same location. </ul>
        <h2>Refreshing Aspects</h2> 
        <p1>In addition to adding new aspects, free invokes may be refreshed (cleared off so they may be invoked for free again) on aspects in play using the Create and Advantage action. The procedure is the same – make a relevant skill check against a difficulty based on the duration of the aspect.</p1> 
        <ul>•	Tie or Success. Aspect has one free invoke. •	Succeed with Style. Aspect has two free invokes.</ul> 
        <p1>o Overcome Obstacle This is the most common action taken during the narrative phase, and also is used in a variety of ways during each mini-game. The process is fairly general – roll against some opposition. During the mini-games, this action may be used to remove an aspect from play. If this aspect is actively being maintained by another character, then getting rid of it will involve active opposition.  </p1>
        <p1>The results depend on the outcome of a 4dF + skill roll, compared to the difficulty.</p1> 
        <ul>•	Fail. The default is that the player fails their action. Failing this action during the narrative phase involves other penalties. See the Missions chapter for more details. •	Tie. On a tie, the player may create a boost, related somehow to the use of the skill. •	Success. The player makes progress towards completing the obstacle. If the target was an aspect, it is removed from play. If the target had a stress track, add stress to the stress track equal to the number of shifts. •	Succeed with Style. Same as the general success case, but the player may create a boost as well. </ul>
        <h3>Removing Aspects</h3> 
        <p1>If the aspect was created by a character, removing it may merit active opposition. For instance, getting rid of the thief’s Hiding in the Shadows might be opposed by his Stealth skill.</p1> 
        <p1>However, if no skills apply and there aren’t any listed difficulties by the GM, the difficulty is two, plus two more for each free invoke. So, an aspect that has two free invokes would have an opposition of 6 to Overcome.</p1> 
        <p1>aAttack The attack action isn’t used during the narrative phase. It occurs fairly frequently during the mini-games. Note that the attack action is very broad in use. It covers not just physical attacks, but could involve a volley of arrows from a unit, or a hero attempting to seduce a character. It’s any action where the target is another character and the goal is to inflict physical or mental stress.</p1> 
        <p1>The results depend on the outcome of a 4dF + skill roll, compared to a 4dF + skill roll made by the opponent. The skills to use depend on the context, for instance, Intimidation might be opposed by Will, while Fighting might be opposed by Fighting, etc. The Skills chapter and the various mini-game chapters contain many suggestions.</p1> 
        <ul>•	Fail. Unsuccessful attack. If the player fails by three or more, the opponent (defender) gets to create a boost! •	Tie. On a tie, the player may create a boost, related to the attack. •	Success. The target takes stress equal to the number of shifts rolled. •	Succeed with Style. Same as the general success case, but the attacker may create a boost as well. </ul>
        <h3>Taking Stress</h3> 
        <p1>Attacks frequently result in a character taking stress. Note that anything in the game with a stress track (narrative obstacles, certain elements in Warfare) takes stress in the same fashion.</p1> 
        <p1>When stress is taken, the target may fill in one open box on an applicable stress track to lower stress. The stress is reduced by an amount equal to the position of the open stress box filled in on the track. </p1>
        <p1>Example: Catrin is hit by an Ogre’s club and takes three physical stress. She fills in the second physical stress box on her track, which lowers the amount of stress taken by two. She still has one stress remaining. If this doesn’t get rid of all the stress, open consequences may be filled in to get rid of the rest. The level of the consequence determines the amount of stress that is reduced in this way. A minor consequence can take two stress, a major can take four, and a severe can take six.</p1> 
        <p1>Example: Next, Catrin uses her minor consequence slot, which is still open to reduce the remaining stress point. She writes Bruised Arm in her minor consequence slot. This lowers the stress taken by two, getting rid of the remaining stress. The ogre (or some other character) can use the free invoke on this new consequence in order to do more damage to Catrin later.</p1> 
        <p1>If a character or target can’t negate the stress by filling in one box on a relevant stress track and taking any number of consequences, they are taken out. This can mean different things, depending on the mini-game, but usually means they are not available anymore in the campaign.</p1>    

    </Story>

</Root>
