<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<Root><Story><chapter>Infiltration</chapter> <p1>Infiltration is used for covert operations targeting a physical installation (called <term>the house</term>). It is the conflict used for Assassination and Sabotage missions. Whether stealing secret arcane formulae or laying waste to an ore refinery, the most important part of Infiltration is the ability to carry out the plan without being detected or using a large force.</p1>   <p1>The heroes must sneak through the target location, avoiding or deceiving guards, while overcoming a number of security challenges in the process. Failing rolls during the conflict may arouse the suspicion of nearby guards, or even cause the guards to sound the alarm. Infiltration is not without risk. It is possible for one or more of the heroes to get caught in that act, leading to potentially dire consequences.</p1> <h1nb>Challenges</h1nb> <p1>During the challenge phase, the Stronghold players case the house, working to get access as well as uncover details about the target. Finding a safe house and uncovering different contacts are also good challenges for the challenge phase.</p1> <p1>All of these details eventually feed into a plan which is played out in the conflict. In essence, the challenges help to define the sorts of elements that the group finds interesting, and these will become important during the conflict. The challenges can also take the form of questions, the answers to which help flesh out the house.</p1> <p1>Be careful to not prematurely start playing through the conflict. That is, the challenges should be questions about the target, but shouldn’t actually involve directly accomplishing the mission (stealing the plans, assassinating the target, etc). That is covered during the conflict. Instead, this is the time to think about the house. What does it look like? What features and vulnerabilities does it have? Who can access it?</p1> <h1nb>Opposition</h1nb> <p1>Most of the opposition comes from <b>guards</b>, minions that try to detect the heroes. If the mission involves a faction, a leader from the faction may take the place of one of the guards.</p1> <h2>Creating Guards</h2> <p1>Guards are built as minions with a skill cap equal to the mission difficulty. Notice and Empathy skills are good to help detect intruders, and Athletics and Fighting are good to detain them. Giving guards a higher Fighting skill helps push the action toward stealth and fast talking, as overt aggression becomes riskier.</p1> <h2>Sample Guards</h2> <p1>These sample guards can be chosen from as desired. It’s easiest if all the guards share the same template, but what guards to use is up to the Autarch player.</p1> <statblock><p1></p1><Table xmlns:aid="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/4.0/" aid:table="table" aid:trows="11" aid:tcols="2"><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="2"><strong>Standard Guard</strong> </Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="88.29999999999998"><b>Type</b></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="174.70000000000002">Minion</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="88.29999999999998"><b>Physical</b></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="174.70000000000002"><fate>2</fate></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="88.29999999999998"><b>Mental</b></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="174.70000000000002"><fate>3</fate></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="88.29999999999998"><b>Superb (+5)</b></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="174.70000000000002">Fighting</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="88.29999999999998"><b>Great (+4)</b></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="174.70000000000002">Empathy</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="88.29999999999998"><b>Good (+3)</b></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="174.70000000000002">Notice</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="88.29999999999998"><b>Decent (+2)</b></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="174.70000000000002">Will</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="88.29999999999998"><b>Average (+1)</b></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="174.70000000000002">Athletics</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="2"><aspect>Lives to Crack Heads</aspect> <aspect>Slow Moving Brute</aspect></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="2"><strong>Torch - </strong>Step up the help die when using Notice to detect stealthy intruders.</Cell></Table></statblock> <p1>Standard guards have a higher Fighting and Will, so that the use of stealthy means of success are encouraged.﻿</p1> <statblock><p1></p1><Table xmlns:aid="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/4.0/" aid:table="table" aid:trows="11" aid:tcols="2"><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="2"><strong>Observant Guard</strong> </Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="88.29999999999998"><b>Type</b></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="174.70000000000002">Minion</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="88.29999999999998"><b>Physical</b></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="174.70000000000002"><fate>2</fate></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="88.29999999999998"><b>Mental</b></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="174.70000000000002"><fate>2</fate></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="88.29999999999998"><b>Superb (+5)</b></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="174.70000000000002">Notice</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="88.29999999999998"><b>Great (+4)</b></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="174.70000000000002">Empathy</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="88.29999999999998"><b>Good (+3)</b></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="174.70000000000002">Athletics</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="88.29999999999998"><b>Decent (+2)</b></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="174.70000000000002">Fighting</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="88.29999999999998"><b>Average (+1)</b></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="174.70000000000002">Marksmanship</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="2"><aspect>“Halt! Who goes there?”</aspect> <aspect>“When’s Lunch?”</aspect></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="2"><strong>Sense Motive - </strong>Step up the help die when using Empathy to detect lies.</Cell></Table></statblock> <p1>Observant guards are good at detecting intruders, but are more susceptible to attack.﻿</p1> <h1>Setup</h1> <p1>The players collaboratively come up with a plan, making a map of the house, and then placing the heroes, initial guards, and alarms.</p1> <h2>Security Challenges</h2> <p1>As the heroes go through the challenge phase, the players create details about the house. These details form the basis of the plan. The heroes are huddled over the table at the back of the inn, drawing out who goes where and when to accomplish the task.</p1> <p1>Mechanically, each stage in the plan is represented as a <term>security challenges</term>. These work the same way the challenges work in the challenge phase, with a few small restrictions. The players must create one security challenge for each hero on the mission. Each security challenge is written on a separate note card. Above each security challenge, write a location within the house where the challenge takes place. The difficulty of each challenge is equal to the difficulty of the mission (they aren’t rolled for like in the challenge phase).</p1> <p1>Finally, unlike the challenges in the challenge phase, which are fairly open ended in terms of what skills can be used to overcome them, security challenges have a skill restriction. This restriction means that only the listed skill may be used to Overcome the challenge. In addition, the following skills must be used at least once: Thievery, Stealth, and Deceive. The other skills are left up to the Stronghold players. For example, <aspect>Main Office: <fate>2</fate> Crack the Vault - Thievery</aspect>, or <aspect>Library: <fate>2</fate> Distract Baron von Schlefwitz - Deceive</aspect>.</p1> <h2>Create the Map</h2> <p1>Gather together the security challenge note cards, and add an additional number of note cards equal to the number of players. These form the zones of the house.</p1> <p1>The Autarch player and the spotlight player take turns placing the note cards onto the table. The Autarch player goes first, choosing any desired note card, followed by the spotlight player. Note cards must be placed orthogonally to one or more other note cards. Finally, a note card is placed by the Autarch player, with the zone label <aspect>Outside the House</aspect>.</p1> <p1>Blank note cards may be given zone names by the players as desired (<aspect>The Hall</aspect>, <aspect>The Courtyard</aspect>, etc).</p1> <h2>Place Alarms</h2> <p1>The Autarch player may write the aspect <aspect>Alarm</aspect> on a number of zones equal to half the heroes (round down as usual).</p1> <h2>Place Guards</h2> <p1>The Autarch player starts with a number of guards equal to half the heroes (round down). Each guard is placed on the edge of one of the note cards. It’s fine to place multiple cards on the same zone.</p1> <h2>Starting Fate Points</h2> <p1>The Autarch player starts the conflict with fate points equal to the number of heroes. These can be spent on any guard as desired.</p1> <h2>Aspect Burning</h2> <p1>Each free invoke burned can be used to allow a hero unrestricted access to a zone (by default heroes are not allowed in any zones) or add a new zone to the map.</p1> <h1>Actions</h1> <p1>When a character takes a turn, they choose one of the actions from the list below. Some actions are only available to heroes while some are only available to the opposition leaders.</p1> <h2>Exchange</h2> <p1>Each hero takes an action in any order desired by the spotlight player. Next, each guard (or leader) takes one action in any order desired by the Autarch player. Finally, more guards may arrive.</p1> <h2>Suspicion and Alert</h2> <p1>If a hero fails any action, the nearest guard gets the aspect <aspect>Suspicious</aspect> with one free invoke. If instead any guards are in the same zone as the hero when the action is failed, each guard in the zone gets the aspect <aspect>Alerted!</aspect> with two free invokes.</p1>  <h2>Create an Advantage</h2> <p1>Any player may attempt to create a minor advantage during their turn, following the normal rules for Create an Advantage in the <chapref>Fate</chapref> chapter. Remember that aspects which directly target specific characters should be actively opposed, rather than using the passive difficulty.</p1> <h2>Overcome</h2> <p1>Players may use Overcome to remove aspects, as well as take one of the actions below.</p1> <h3>Remove Suspicion and Alerts</h3> <p1>Since these are just aspects, a hero can attempt to use Overcome to get rid of them, resulting in the guard going back to a normal state. This can typically be done using Deceive (opposed by Empathy). If the alarm has been raised, this action is not available.</p1> <h3>Detect Intruder</h3> <p1>Guards may attempt to a detect a hero in the same zone. Typical skills used are Notice (opposed by Stealth) or Empathy (opposed by Deceive).</p1> <h3>Overcome Security Challenge</h3> <p1>This works basically as it does for the challenge phase. However, the Stronghold players never get narrative control and may not bring in new challenges. But the challenge takes stress in the same fashion if the hero succeeds, and the hero takes stress if they fail.</p1> <h3>Movement</h3> <p1>Unopposed heroes may move one zone and take a different action, or move up to their maximum movement rate. Heroes must stop movement when entering a zone with a guard or the guard becomes alerted.</p1> <p1>Guards <b>patrol</b>, moving only one zone each exchange in the direction they’re facing, turning around when they run out of room. Place guards at one edge of the note card they’re on to indicate the direction they will move next turn. Suspicious and alerted guards move as heroes do.</p1>  <h2>Attack</h2> <p1>Both guards and heroes may attack using any of the normally available skills (Fighting, Marksmanship, and Intimidation). If a guard is attacked, the immediately gain the <aspect>Alerted!</aspect> aspect with two free invokes.</p1> <p1>Since guards are minions, they work best if they work together to attack a hero.</p1> <h3>Dead Guards</h3> <p1>If a guard is killed, the body remains in the zone. If another guard enters the zone, they become alerted.</p1>  <h2>Defend</h2> <p1>The standard skills are available to defend with (Athletics defends against Fighting or Marksmanship, Fighting defends against Fighting, and Will defends against Intimidation).</p1> <h2>Raise the Alarm</h2> <p1>If a guard ends their action in a zone with an alarm, the alarm is sounded. All guards become alerted, and may move and attack freely.</p1> <h2>More Guards</h2> <p1>After each exchange, the Autarch player may place one guard in any zone if there are fewer guards than heroes. If the alarm has sounded, this restriction is removed, and one guard is placed after each exchange regardless of the number of guards currently placed.</p1> <h1>Resolution</h1> <p1>The heroes are successful when all the security challenges are completed and at least one hero makes it back <aspect>Outside the House</aspect>.</p1> <p1>If any heroes are caught, the disposition of the faction drops as listed in the mission description (one for Espionage, two for Sabotage, and three for Assassination). Furthermore, the captured hero is imprisoned or killed (imprisoned for four seasons for Espionage or killed if caught during Sabotage or Assassination).</p1></Story></Root>
