<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<!DOCTYPE Root SYSTEM "BookChapter.dtd">
<Root> 
    <Story>
        <chapter>Magic</chapter>
        <p1>Among the many resources the land produces, the most potent is also the most difficult to detect and harness.  There is a force, called mana, which flows out from the most wild and untamed parts of the wilderness.</p1>
        <p1>Through the use of Channeling mana may be detected and harnessed, and through the use of Spellcraft and secrets, it may be released to produce an effect.  Secrets function almost identically to Stunts, with each Secret granting access to an array of effects all related thematically.</p1>
        <h1>Capturing Mana</h1>
        Mana is present everywhere, although in some locations, it is present in high enough concentration to be harnessed by characters who have ranks in the Channeling skill.  Retrieving mana from the land is a very slow and solitary process.  For each full season a character spends in a region, they gain at most the mana value of the region to their pool.  
        The maximum amount of mana which may be drawn from the land is equal to the character’s mana skill times three.  So, the mana attribute of a region reflects how long it takes to draw mana from the region.  A region with zero mana is effectively barren in terms of mana, only containing trace amounts which can’t be harnessed.
        As described Seasons chapter, characters may be assigned to regions during the upkeep stage after a mission.  Only characters that didn’t go on the mission may be assigned to a region to harness mana (it takes the entire season).  The region where the character’s mana comes from should also be noted on the character sheet.  
        Example: Kara is sent to the Sunset Isles during the Fall to harness mana.  The Sunset Isles have two mana, Kara’s Channeling skill is four and her current total mana is six. After this season, her total mana is raised by two to eight.  The most mana Kara can have at once is twelve (three times her Channeling). 
        Gathering mana is a slow process.  Frequently channelers are very solitary, taking solace in understanding the flora and fauna of the region they spend so much time in.  Drawing in mana from the land makes the character part of the land.  If the land is altered or marred in a significant fashion, the mana may be lost, and the character may become injured.  Similarly, if the mana is used incorrectly or too quickly, the land may be affected.  This can occur from backlash as well as altered from various developments.
        Restrictions
        When mana is channeled from a region, the region is noted on the character sheet, next to the character’s mana pool.  It isn’t possible for a channeler to retrieve mana from more than one region, as the effort required to create bonds with the land is too great.  Thus, if a character is bound to one region and tries to channel from another, their mana pools starts at zero again.
        Furthermore, only one channeler may operate in a region at any time.  Multiple channelers may be bound to the same region, but only one can pull in mana during any particular season.
        Casting Spells
        In order to use magic, the character needs to have access to mana and a secret.  Mana is used as fuel to power an effect.
        One way to gain mana is to use the Channeling skill and spend time in a region harnessing the magic there.  There are other ways, however, such as through the use of conduits, physical artifacts which have the magic of the land harnessed in them.  Secrets work like stunts (they are tied to the Spellcraft skill) and are described in more detail later in the chapter.
        Casting Check and Backlash Check
        Each Secret describes what occurs when mana expenditure happens.  Generally, the more mana spent, the more powerful the effect.  In order to trigger any effect, at least one mana must be spent.   The first step is to choose an effect and spend the mana.  
        For some spells, a casting check is necessary.  This check is usually 4dF + Spellcraft, although sometimes other modifiers, such as the mana spent, are added to the roll.  The Secret describes what the result of the casting check accomplishes.  The listed effect always occurs; there isn’t a way to fail a casting check.  Rather, it just determines how powerful the effect is.  This effect takes place immediately.  
        Spending too much mana could result in terrible backlash.  Any time more mana is spent on a casting check than the character’s Channeling skill; the player rolls 4dF + Channeling, and compares it to the amount of mana spent.  This is called the backlash check.  Fate points may not be spent to alter the check.  Backlash occurs from the release of large amounts of magical energy.   This backlash can take a variety of forms, based on the secret.
        Blight
        The land and the caster are intimately connected.  If too much mana is expended during the casting of a spell, the region where the mana came from may become changed; taking on features which are related to the effect produced which caused the mana drain.  Suggestions for the nature of the blights are given in the secret descriptions.
        For each point below the target number on the backlash check, one resource (food, timber, ore, mana, or luxuries) is removed from the land, chosen by the caster.  
        Furthermore, after all resources are lost, the land gains a new aspect, as it becomes wild and untamed, the mana turning into bizarre physical features.  Choose wisely the lands where you draw mana from, as a region with no resources isn’t very valuable!
        Madness
        In addition to the land, mana also binds people together.  This is how channelers are able to detect emotions and feelings in others.  This allows some secrets to function better when they have a relationship with the target.  Spells with madness backlash can cause stress damage to one of the caster’s loved ones. 
        Each point below the backlash opposition results in two points of stress for the character that is closest to the caster.  This should be spelled out on the relationship list.  The target may not use their stress track to help absorb the stress hit – all the stress must be taken as consequences.
        The nature of the consequences is described in more detail under each particular secret.  The nature of the madness relates to the secret which caused them, although the effect is mental.  It is up to the players to decide how the character might react to the stress.  If the character is a hero, the consequences should be noted on the character sheet.
        Anarchy
        The final type of blight comes from the Stronghold itself.  Some spells cause backlash to the stability of the Stronghold.  For these powerful secrets, each point below the backlash opposition causes one points of stability loss for the Stronghold.
 
        Spell Effects
        The descriptions for the secrets elaborate each of the different effects they have.  Most powers have some associated mana cost, and require a casting check.
        Base Effect
        One option available to most secrets is to spend a point of mana in order to use Spellcraft to function as a skill related to the Secret.  This is common in the narrative phase, but it could happen in the mini-games as well.
        Example: Kara is attacked by wolves, and spends one point of mana to use her Secret of Fire to roll Spellcraft in order to injure them.
        In addition, extra mana may be spent as Fate points to modify this roll (add +2 or re-roll as fate points do).  Spending mana doesn’t require invoking an aspect (so lots of mana may be spent on the same roll).  The backlash is determined by adding up the total mana spent.
        Without spending mana, Spellcraft can’t be used to produce effects related to the secret.  It will just function as per the skill description (for knowledge related to arcane lore). 
        Secrets
        Each secret functions just like a stunt.  In the secret description, there is a listing of the variety of effects produced when different amounts of mana are expended.  The other important part of the descriptions is the nature of the madness which occurs during a mishap.
 
        Secret of Desire
        The caster can control wants and desires, from the whims and wishes of a single person up to the leanings and attitudes of an entire population of people.
        Backlash: Anarchy
        On failed backlash checks, the Secret of Desire causes strife and discord to spread within the Stronghold.
        Base Effect
        By spending a point of mana, the caster may substitute their Spellcraft for any social roll (those relying on Rapport, Deceive, or Intimidate).
        Initiate Effects
        Fear (Warfare)
        Minimum Mana Cost: 5
        Caster may target a unit in combat, making a Spellcraft check against their Will. Positive shifts are taken as morale stress by the targeted unit.
        If the unit is routed in battle, it is not lost.
        Adept Effects
        Mood of a Nation (Diplomacy)
        Minimum Mana Cost: 10
        The caster channels mana in order to change the will of the people in a faction.  This effect may not be used on any faction who has a disposition of -5.
        Caster Check	Disposition Change
<16	+1
        16-20	+2
        21-25	+3
        25>	+4

 
        Secret of Fire
        The caster can control flame.  From starting simple fires to burning down entire villages, fire is an extension of the will of the caster.
        Backlash: Blight
        The land turns into a blighted wasteland.  Permanent molten pits dot the landscape, and frighteningly hot temperatures thwart inhabitants.
        Base Effect
        By spending a point of mana, the caster may substitute their Spellcraft for rolls involving attacking people with fire (either Marksmanship or Fighting).
        Initiate Effects
        Wall of Fire (Warfare)
        Mana Cost: 5
        As an action, the caster my make a ranged attack on a unit, substituting the caster’s Spellcraft skill for the unit’s Marksmanship skill.
        Adept Effects
        Inferno (Warfare)
        Mana Cost: 10
        As Wall of Fire, except every unit in the target zone is affected.
        Master Effects
        Focused Blast (Warfare)
        Mana Cost: 15
        Target two zones on the battlefield.  Everything within the two zones is destroyed, including units, leaders, and any fortifications such as castles or keeps.
 
        Secret of Life
        The caster can heal the sick, remove wounds, and at the highest mana expenditures, they can even resurrect an entire unit of troops.
        Backlash: Madness
        The character friendly to the caster becomes dead inside.  Withdrawn and distant, shunning human contact.  At the extreme end, they may become completely catatonic, unable or unwilling to motivate themselves to any action whatsoever.
        Resist Blow (Any)
        The caster may spend a mana point to reduce any physical stress taken by four.
        Heal Wounds (Any)
        Minimum Mana Cost: 1
        The caster may spend mana to heal the sick or wounded of consequences that have a physical cause.  This takes one action.  
        Make a caster check, and choose a consequence on a target.  If the caster check is equal to or greater than twice the strength (4, 8, or 12) of the consequence, it is removed.  For example, a caster check of 12 would be necessary to remove a severe consequence.
        Master Effect
        Raise the Dead (Season)
        Mana Cost: 15
        At the end of any season, the caster may expend 16 mana to resurrect a deceased hero.  This decision is ultimately up to the spotlight player for the session.  Note that the caster isn’t required to go on any mission for the season.  Of course, mana is spent and subtracted from the character’s sheet as normal.
 
        <h1>Designer’s Notes</h1>
        <p1>The effect of mana exponentially increases at higher levels, and is based on the difficulty it takes to increase skills from 0 to 18.  For any particular secret, there are smoothing operations done so that the units and effects are easier to manage, but each secret is based on the power curve listed in the table below.  If you wish to design your own secrets, this table can serve as a rough guide for effects.  For instance, if we take 1 mana expenditure to be 1 ft of range, 18 mana would be roughly 3.88 miles.</p1>
        <p1>Mana Spent	Power	Distance (Example)
            1-2	1	1 ft.
            3-5	2	2 ft.
            6-8	15	15 ft.
            9-11	84	84 ft.
            12-14	470	156 yards
            15-17	2910	970 yards
            18	20517	3.88 miles</p1>
        <h2>Dramatic Scenes</h2>
        <p1>Maybe a point of mana should function like a Fate Point in dramatic scenes, with the added caveat that it must relate to the Secret?</p1>      
    </Story>
</Root>
