<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<!DOCTYPE Root SYSTEM "BookChapter.dtd">
<Root> 
    <Story>
        <chapter>Magic</chapter>
        <p1>Magic is the fusion of mana and the spellcaster's will, a process known as channeling. Mana is chaotic and omnipresent froce of energy, difficult to control but powerful. It is present everywhere, although in some locations, the untamed and exotic parts of the wilds, it is present in high enough concentration to be harnessed by magic users. Characters with high enough <skill>Lore</skill> may learn <term>Secrets</term>, complex and arcane procedures for channeling mana to produce all manner of fantastical effects.</p1>
        <h1>Mana</h1>
        <p1>Mana, for those with attuned channeling abilities, appears as shimmering bands of color, like a tinted hue laid out upon the land. Each region generates its own unique signature of mana, and capable channelers can detect the origin of mana that has been channeled by casters. It can be stored and bound in a wide variety of vessels, although this greatly weaks its potency, making it worthless for use in spells.</p1> 
        <h2>Binding to the Land</h2>
        <p1>Before wielding Secrets, a spellcaster must <term>bind</term> to the land. This is an involved process, taking an entire season to accomplish (newly made characters may start play already bound to a region). This is also a solitary time, as the caster takes solace in understanding the flore and fauna of the region. The caster becomes part of the land, in an intimate relationship. The caster will be acutely aware of when the land is damaged or when another caster is attempting to bind to the same region.</p1> 
        <p1>The regions with the highest amount of mana allow for the most potent use of magic. When a caster binds to a region, the region is noted on the character sheet, next to the character’s mana pool. It isn’t possible for a channeler to bind to more than one region, as the effort required to create bonds with the land is too great. A caster may change which region they are bound to, but this takes an entire season of time (no training or healing is possible).</p1>
        <h2>Starting Mana</h2>
        <p1>At the start of each season, every character bound to the land gains an amount of mana equal to their Channeling skill times the mana value of the region divided by two (as usual, round any fractions down).</p1>
        <example>Kara is bound to the Sunset Isles. The Sunset Isles have two mana, along with a Mana Forge (increasing mana there by one for channeling). Kara’s Channeling skill is four. She will start each season with 4 * 3 = 12 / 2 = 6 mana.</example>        
        <h1>Wielding Magic</h1>
        <p1>In order to use magic, a character needs to be bound to a region and have a high enough <skill>Lore</skill> skill to gain access to a Secret. Mana is then expended based on the specific Secret and effect desired, as outlined below.</p1>
        <h2>Secrets</h2>
        <p1>Secrets are groupings of thematically linked stunts. Each Secret has four stunts, the four tiers of increasing mystical knowledge with the Secret. These tiers, in order of increasing power, are known as <term>Initiate</term>, <term>Apprentice</term>, <term>Journeyman</term>, and <term>Keeper</term>. Earlier tiered stunts are prerequisites for later tiered stunts. For instance, a character must have the Apprentice level stunt in the Secret of the Elements (Hailstorm) before being able to gain the Journeyman Secret of the Elements stunt (Wind Rider).</p1>
        <p1>Although it's possible to become an Initiate in multiple Secrets, thus gaining a broad ability, the only way to gain access to the very powerful Keeper stunts is to specialize. Specialists tend to be defined by their Secret. Each Secret tends to be linked with a worldview and ethos that is a core part of the caster.</p1>               
        <h3>Initiate Tier</h3>
        <p1>One option available to most secrets is to spend a point of mana in order to use Spellcraft to function as a skill related to the Secret.  This is common in the narrative phase, but it could happen in the mini-games as well.</p1>
        <example>Kara is attacked by wolves, and spends one point of mana to use her Secret of Fire to roll Spellcraft in order to injure them.</example>
        <p1>In addition, extra mana may be spent as Fate points to modify this roll (add +2 or re-roll as fate points do).  Spending mana doesn’t require invoking an aspect (so lots of mana may be spent on the same roll).  The backlash is determined by adding up the total mana spent.</p1>
        <p1>Without spending mana, Spellcraft can’t be used to produce effects related to the secret.  It will just function as per the skill description (for knowledge related to arcane lore).</p1>      
        <h3>Advanced Tiers</h3>
        <p1>Advanced Tiers have set mana costs, and produce the described effects. General effects?</p1>
        <h2>Casting Check</h2>
        <p1>Each Secret describes what occurs when mana expenditure happens.  Generally, the more mana spent, the more powerful the effect.  In order to trigger any effect, at least one mana must be spent.   The first step is to choose an effect and spend the mana.</p1> 
        <p1>For some spells, a casting check is necessary.  This check is usually 4dF + Spellcraft, although sometimes other modifiers, such as the mana spent, are added to the roll.  The Secret describes what the result of the casting check accomplishes.  The listed effect always occurs; there isn’t a way to fail a casting check.  Rather, it just determines how powerful the effect is.  This effect takes place immediately.</p1> 
        <p1>Spending too much mana could result in terrible backlash.  Any time more mana is spent on a casting check than the character’s Channeling skill; the player rolls 4dF + Channeling, and compares it to the amount of mana spent.  This is called the backlash check.  Fate points may not be spent to alter the check.  Backlash occurs from the release of large amounts of magical energy.   This backlash can take a variety of forms, based on the secret.</p1>        
        <h2>Backlash Check</h2>
        <h2>Backlash Effects</h2>
        <p1>The land and the caster are intimately connected.  If too much mana is expended during the casting of a spell, the region where the mana came from may become changed; taking on features which are related to the effect produced which caused the mana drain.  Suggestions for the nature of the blights are given in the secret descriptions.</p1>
        <p1>For each point below the target number on the backlash check, one resource (food, timber, ore, mana, or luxuries) is removed from the land, chosen by the caster.</p1>  
        <p1>Furthermore, after all resources are lost, the land gains a new aspect, as it becomes wild and untamed, the mana turning into bizarre physical features.  Choose wisely the lands where you draw mana from, as a region with no resources isn’t very valuable!</p1>        
        <h1>Secrets of the Dead</h1>
        <stuntt>Shadow Walker</stuntt>
        <stuntd>Stealth, realm of the dead.</stuntd>
        <stuntt>Commune with the Dead</stuntt>
        <stuntd>Create aspects with three free invokes.</stuntd>
        <stuntt>Animate Dead</stuntt>
        <stuntd>Raise a fallen character, weaker and changed.</stuntd>
        <stuntt>Army of the Dead</stuntt>
        <stuntd>Infantry of the dead.</stuntd>
        <h1>Secrets of the Elements</h1>
        <p1>The caster can control flame. From starting simple fires to burning down entire villages, fire is an extension of the will of the caster.</p1>        
        <stuntt>Fire Strike</stuntt>
        <stuntd>Marksmanships, attack with fire.</stuntd>
        <stuntt>Hailstorm</stuntt>
        <stuntd>Multiple targets with hail.</stuntd>
        <stuntt>Wind Rider</stuntt>
        <stuntd>Move quickly, leave/enter outside zones.</stuntd>
        <stuntt>Earthquake</stuntt>
        <stuntd>Destroy keep, castle, units and leaders take massive damage.</stuntd>
        <h1>Secrets of the Mind</h1>
        <p1>The caster can control wants and desires, from the whims and wishes of a single person up to the leanings and attitudes of an entire population of people.</p1>        
        <stuntt>Web of Lies</stuntt>
        <stuntd>Deceive, lies.</stuntd>
        <stuntt>Glamour</stuntt>
        <stuntd>Target subtracts from Notice and Empathy tests.</stuntd>
        <stuntt>Paragon of Grace</stuntt>
        <stuntd>Add lore to rapport and society.</stuntd>
        <stuntt>Collective Will</stuntt>
        <stuntd>Minor faction becomes an ally.</stuntd>
        <h1>Secrets of the Wilds</h1>
        <stuntt>Primal Quickness</stuntt>
        <stuntd>Athletics, quicker movement.</stuntd>
        <stuntt>Fangs of the Wolf</stuntt>
        <stuntd>Skirmish creature.</stuntd>
        <stuntt>Skin of the Snake</stuntt>
        <stuntd>Infiltration creature.</stuntd>
        <stuntt>Heart of the Dragon</stuntt>
        <stuntd>Warfare creature.</stuntd>
        <h1>Designer’s Notes</h1>
        <p1>The effect of mana exponentially increases at higher levels, and is (loosely) based on the difficulty it takes to improve the skill pyramid. For any particular secret, there are smoothing operations done so that the units and effects are easier to manage, but each secret is based on the power curve listed in the table below. If you wish to design your own secrets, this table can serve as a rough guide for effects. For instance, if we take 1 mana expenditure to be 1 ft of range, 18 mana would be roughly 3.88 miles.</p1>
        <table xmlns:aid="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/4.0/" aid:table="table" aid:trows="8" aid:tcols="3">
            <cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">Mana Spent</cell>
            <cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">Power</cell>
            <cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">Distance</cell>
            <cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">1-2</cell>
            <cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">1</cell>
            <cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">1 ft.</cell>   
            <cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">3-5</cell>
            <cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">2</cell>
            <cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">2 ft.</cell> 
            <cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">6-8</cell>
            <cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">15</cell>
            <cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">15 ft.</cell> 
            <cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">9-11</cell>
            <cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">84</cell>
            <cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">84 ft.</cell> 
            <cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">12-14</cell>
            <cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">470</cell>
            <cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">156 yards</cell>
            <cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">15+</cell>
            <cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">2910</cell>
            <cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="131.5">970 yards</cell>           
        </table>  
    </Story>
</Root>
