<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<Root>
    <Story>
        <chapter>Missions</chapter> 
        <p1>Missions are the bread and butter of Wrath of the Autarch. While the people who make up the Stronghold undertake all sorts of activites during a season, only the missions of the heroes are played out in detail. The Stronghold players choose one mission each season, usually at the end of the previous season. Each type of mission has certain benefits as well as possible costs. Besides a key part in the formation of a strategy, selecting missions gets everyone on the same page for what’s going on that session. If the Stronghold players choose a Trade mission, they can be confident a fight won’t break out. By choosing a mission, the players are declaring what is important for the Stronghold to focus on.</p1> 
        <p1>There are eight types of missions available for players to choose: Exploration, Trade, Conquest, Espionage, Sabotage, Assassination, Quest, and Threat. Each of these mission types is not always available for the players to pick. For instance, if the heroes don’t know the location of any artifacts, they may not go on a Quest.</p1> 
        <h1>Structure</h1> 
        <p1>Missions are composed of a <term>Challenge Phase</term> followed by a type of <term>Conflict</term> (either <term>Diplomacy</term>, <term>Infiltration</term>, <term>Skirmish</term>, or <term>Warfare</term>). Mechanically, the Challenge Phase and the Conflict are resolved differently, although there are some similarities common to both. There are some additional steps taken before and after the mission, as outlined below.</p1> 
        <h2>Challenge Phase</h2> 
        <p1>The Challenge Phase uses the same mechanics for every type of mission. During the Challenge Phase involves the players set up scenes and Challenges for the heroes to deal with. The Stronghold players may also create aspects to use in the Conflict or even in future missions. Time scales tend to be very fluid during the Challenge Phase, as all the players can exert considerable narrative control on the story, using flashbacks and cutscenes as desired to frame the story.</p1> 
        <p1>The Conflict chosen largely depends on the sort of mission that is undertaken by the players. The rules for the Conflict are more constraining than they are for the Challenge Phase, which provides for more tactical options.</p1> 
        <p1>There are four different Conflicts: Diplomacy, Skirmish, Infiltration, and Warfare. Skirmishes involve fighting small battles between characters and other opponents, commonly part of Exploration, Quest, and Regional Threat missions. Diplomacy is .  Infiltration naturally occurs during Espionage or Sabotage missions, but could also be a part of Conquest. Finally, Warfare is commonly the province of Military missions.  The Threat missions can feature any of the Conflict types, depending on the nature of the threat.  Each of these four Conflicts has a chapter dedicated to it.</p1> 
        <h2>Conflict</h2> 
        <p1>Following the Challenge Phase is a Conflict. Each type of Conflict is described in its own chapter (<chapref>Infiltration</chapref>, <chapref>Diplomacy</chapref>, <chapref>Skirmish</chapref>, and <chapref>Warfare</chapref>). It is necessary to read over the particular Conflict rules before running a mission which uses them.</p1> 
        <p1>The choice of Conflict can have an impact on the theme of the Challenge Phase. The chapters for the Conflicts have suggestions and notes on how to handle the Challenge Phase leading up to that Conflict.</p1> 
        <h2>Remove Stress</h2> 
        <p1>After the mission is over, all the stress taken by the heroes is removed. Alsoe remove any minor consequences taken (minor consequences only last until the end of the mission). The moderate and severe consequences take longer to heal, requiring the character to rest and recuperate. This is discussed more in the <chapref>Seasons</chapref> and <chapref>Characters</chapref> chapters.</p1> 
        <h2>Modify an Aspect</h2> 
        <p1>If desired, and dramatically appropriate, a Stronghold player may change one of their hero’s aspects. This is particularly common for relationship aspects.</p1> 
        <h2>Mission Results</h2> 
        <p1>Every mission has repercussions for the Stronghold.  The Stronghold sheet and Factions sheet are updated to reflect these changes at the conclusion of the mission.  Notes may be made on the Chronicle sheet as well in order to remember important details, such as stability and population loss, or notable consequences taken by important characters.</p1> 
        <h1>Choosing a Mission</h1> 
        <p1>Each mission type has a different impact on the Stronghold.  Choosing which mission to go on for a particular season is an important part of the strategy in WotA.  Each mission type is resolved using one of the four Conflicts.  In some cases a choice may be made on which Conflict to use (for instance, Conquest missions could be resolved using Skirmish, Diplomacy, or Warfare, depending on the neutral region being conquered).</p1> 
        <p1>Following are descriptions of the different missions, including what Conflicts may be used in resolving them and where to find suggestions for narrative Challenges, as well as any noteworthy details. </p1> 
        <p1>As mentioned, the most important element in running a mission is to understand the details of the Conflict to use. Besides the Conflict, coming up with narrative Challenges to use is another big part of the mission.  For the most part, there are already narrative Challenges created for all the types of missions.  However, these narrative Challenges don’t have to be used; if the GM or even a player has a creative idea, run with it!  It is particularly fun to have recurring elements in the Challenge Phase, so that missions feel less episodic.</p1> 
        <h1>Exploration</h1> 
        <p1>Exploration is a way to get new regions added to the Stronghold.  These regions provide much needed resources.  There are ten neutral regions in the game, each with different resources that can be gained from conquering it.  See the Regions chapter for the complete listing.</p1> 
        <p1>Taking over non-neutral regions (attacking another faction) is covered by the Military mission.</p1> 
        <h2>Restrictions</h2> Unless specified by a development, only one region may be conquered per year.  Any region from the neutral regions list in the Regions chapter may be chosen as the target of Conquest. <h2>Narrative Challenges</h2> Every region has sample narrative Challenges listed in the Regions chapter. <h2>Conflict</h2> The type of Conflict to use is region dependent.  Most of the less populated regions require the clearing of foul beasts from the land, thus they use the Skirmish Conflict.   However, there are regions with large native population who must be bargained with (Diplomacy Conflict) as well as regions with hostile forces (Warfare Conflict) that must be thwarted. See the regions chapter for details, as well as the ramifications of success and failure for each of the Conflict types. Success If the heroes of the Stronghold are successful, write the region down onto the Stronghold sheet.  The resources of the region may be harvested starting next season. Failure If the heroes fail to conquer a region, there are no penalties other than the loss of stress on the part of the heroes. <h1>Trade</h1> Trade missions involve trading goods and services with other factions, as well as improving the disposition with the faction.  As mentioned in the Overview chapter, each faction has different goods and services they will provide as well as want to receive. The details of these goods and services are listed in the Factions chapter.  Using these trade charts is a core part of the Diplomacy Conflict, and is described in more detail in the Diplomacy chapter. Restrictions If the disposition of a faction is at -3 or less, no Diplomacy is possible.  For the purposes of the WotA campaign, that faction is a bitter enemy of the Stronghold, and they will not entertain any trades. Narrative Challenges The Factions chapter lists sample Challenges to use during any diplomatic interactions for each faction. Conflict The Diplomacy Conflict is used to resolve Trade missions. Success Success indicates the deal will happen, the results of which take place starting in the following season, and lasting for the duration of the deal.  Furthermore, the disposition with the faction will increase by a point.  See the Diplomacy chapter for more details. Failure Not only will the deal not go through, but the disposition with the faction will drop by a point.  See the Diplomacy chapter for more details. <h1>Conquest</h1> A military mission is direct martial action against another faction, with the purpose of occupying a region through the use of force.  Troops are mustered for both parties, and if the Stronghold successfully occupies certain strategic locations in the region, they gain the region for themselves. Restrictions There are no specific restrictions for employing martial action.  However, having a high population, as well as stability, helps in recruiting units, and having certain military developments certainly makes success more likely.  Furthermore, resources are needed to fund the war effort. Narrative Challenges The Factions chapter has example narrative scenes to use during a Military mission.  Furthermore, the Warfare chapter has some generic narrative Challenges that would apply to any mission which uses Warfare. Conflict Military missions always use the Warfare Conflict. Success If a Military mission is successful, the region that is attacked is under the command of the Stronghold.  Starting next season, the resources may be utilized by the Stronghold.  Even with success, Warfare has potentially high costs in population, stability, and resources. Failure Besides not getting the region, it is possible that both population and stability may decrease, as well as disposition with other factions.  The Warfare chapter has more details. <h1>Espionage</h1> 
        <h1>Sabotage</h1> Espionage and Sabotage missions deal with developments.  Most developments can be targeted, with options dependent on the specific development and type of mission.   Restrictions The first step is to choose a development possessed by another faction.  See the Factions chapter for a listing of all the developments. Next, the Developments chapter may be consulted to find specific options for the development in question.  Generally, there are options to either go on an Espionage mission (stealing secrets to make it cheaper to build) or a Sabotage mission (somehow hampering the development for the target faction). Narrative Challenges Narrative Challenges for Espionage and Sabotage missions are fairly unique, in that they always have the same basic theme.  See the Infiltration chapter for more details. Conflict Espionage and Sabotage missions use the Infiltration Conflict. Success Success depends on the specific development targeted.  For espionage sorts of activities, this usually translates into decreased costs to build the development.  While for sabotage, the target faction usually takes a stability hit, as well as other effects. The Developments chapter lists the effects of Infiltration for each development. Failure Failure takes a few forms in Infiltration missions.  It is possible to fail the mission without having heroes captured.  If heroes are captured, there is a disposition penalty with the target faction.  In addition, capture can result in the imprisonment or death (particularly for Sabotage missions) of the perpetrating heroes.  See the Infiltration and Developments chapter for more details. <h1>Assassination</h1> The goal of an Assassination mission to is to murder someone important within the target faction chosen.  Restrictions Only leaders from the various major factions may be targeted.  See the chapters for each faction for listings of the leadership. Narrative Challenges Narrative Challenges for Assassination missions are probably similar thematically to those used in Espionage and Sabotage missions, since the goal is to get close to a target. Conflict Assassination missions use the Infiltration Conflict if the leader isn’t particularly adept at fighting and the Skirmish Conflict if they have a strong ability to defend themselves.  For more details, see the faction chapters. Success The leader is killed – and thus no longer able to be chosen or used by the faction in any capacity. Failure The results of failure are usually death. <h1>Quest</h1> Quests are missions to retrieve legendary artifacts from remote areas of the Realm.  There are only a small number of quests available, but the possible rewards for success are very powerful. Restrictions The heroes of the Stronghold must learn the location of an artifact before going on a quest.  This is usually done through a Trade mission with a faction, although some developments can reveal quests. Narrative Challenges The narrative Challenges for each quest type are given in the Quests chapter. Conflict Quests most frequently use the Skirmish Conflict, since they involve thwarting a great beast of some sort.  However, there are quests that also require other Conflict types.  The Quests chapter lists what sort of Conflict to use for each quest. Success Success allows the Stronghold to gain an artifact.  The details of what each artifact does are listed in the Quests chapter. Failure There is no additional penalty for failure, other than the stress gained by the heroes and the wasted season. <h1>Threats</h1> Threats are handled a little differently than the other mission types.  Threat missions are driven by chance as well as the GM, and involve potential problems from factions or regions.  Because Threats are not initiated by the players, they may be ignored.  Usually the Stronghold incurs some sort of penalty for ignoring them (commonly in the form of resource and stability loss). Threats come in one of three different types: faction, region, and Autarch.  These Threats all have the same mission structure, but they usually have different repercussions for ignoring them.   Faction Threats are potential areas of discord with a faction, from requests for aid to diplomatic troubles to outright war.  The general result of ignoring faction Threats is a loss of disposition with the faction.  Threats occurring in a region tend to cause problems with the gathering of resources there, whether from marauding beasts or sneaky bandits.  Finally, Autarch Threats tend to worsen as time goes on and the Autarch gains strength.  At the end of each season, the number and type of each Threat is determined.  New threats are added to the Chronicle Sheet. In essence, Threats are the roadblocks in the players’ plans.  These help give the world color and make for tough choices, as the players juggle taking proactive actions that help their long term strategy with reacting to problems that come up Anatomy of a Threat Mission New Threats are determined at the end of each season, as described in the Seasons chapter.  It is one of the last activities performed before the end of a season.  The process is slightly different for faction and region threats than for Autarch threats. Threats potentially use any of the four Conflict types, depending on the specifics of the Threat. Ignoring Threats Unlike the missions driven by the players, Threats have the option to be ignored.  In the description for each Threat mission, the consequences for success, failure, and ignoring the Threat are listed.  Also, ignoring regional threats makes it more likely that regional threats keep recur there. Success and Failure If the Threat missions aren’t ignored, it is possible for the players to either succeed or fail at them.  The main benefit to succeeding at a Threat is to remove the penalties that the Threat mission will cause if it is ignored.  There are rarely benefits to the Stronghold in terms of resources, stability or population. If the Threat mission is related to a region or a faction (not the Autarch), successfully resolving a threat causes the region or faction to become secure for up to two years.  If a region or faction is secure, no new Threats will occur there.  See the Seasons chapter for more details on securing factions and regions. Secure Factions and Regions There are security checkboxes on the Stronghold Sheet in the table for each region and the Faction Sheet for each faction.  When a Threat mission is successful, two of these boxes are filled in (some developments can increase that number).  Every spring, one of these boxes is removed.  Only those regions or factions which don’t have checkboxes will generate Threats. This allows the heroes some measure of calm from a region or faction after successfully dealing with the Threat.  This does not apply to the Autarch, who continually threatens the Stronghold. New Threats See the Seasons chapter for procedures on how to determine if there are threats.  This is checked at the end of each season.</Story>
</Root>
