<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<Root>
    <Story>
        <chapter>Seasons</chapter> 
        <p1>The play of Wrath of the Autarch is grouped by seasons, periods of play where important events are narrated. A season of play is designed to take three or four hours to play, making it a good length of time for the typical session. The main focus of the season is the mission, covered in the next chapter. In addition to the mission, there is some bookkeeping, such as adding up resources acquired and building developments. If necessary, some of the bookkeeping steps could be conducted on a forum or mailing list, shortening the play session even further. Occasionally, this is even ideal, as it lets all the players think about their strategy without being rushed. It is important for seasons to resolve fairly quickly to allow for the epic feel that a kingdom building game needs.</p1> 
        <p1>The term season here is used fairly loosely. A season may take more or less time than three months, and it may be the case that missions overlap somewhat. Although the players undertake only one mission each season, it is assumed that many activities are going on within the Stronghold (such as researching developments). Those activites aren’t worthy of detailed narration. The constraint of one mission each season keeps the pace of the game moving forward and focuses on the big picture. It also makes for tough choices in terms of allocating scarce resources to involved tasks.</p1> 
        <p1>This chapter details the upkeep and development of the Stronghold. It also lists all the steps that book-end a mission. The details of mission structure, as well as the sorts of missions available and what they do for the Stronghold are covered in the next chapter.</p1> 
        <h1>Structure</h1> 
        <p1>Before playing through the chosen mission, resources are harvested and invested in developments and heroes are selected and possibly updated. After the mission, the results of success or failure are applied to the Stronghold. Finally, the effects of any ignored Threats are applied to the Stronghold or appropriate characters.</p1> 
        <h2>Spotlight Player</h2> 
        <p1>Wrath of the Autarch is a game which encourages the players to work together to create a story they’re all interested in telling. However, occasionally there are disagreements. Each session, one player takes on the responsibilities of the spotlight player. This player has the final say in any disagreements for the season. At least as much as resolving disagreements (which probably aren’t that common), the spotlight player also has a larger role in the events of the session, due to additional responsibilities and starting with extra Fate points. As much as possible, the responsibility of spotlight player should rotate among all the players.</p1>  
        <h2>Research Developments</h2> When work begins towards a new development, enter the name of the development on the bottom of the Stronghold Sheet.  Not all developments are literally built, as developments are not just physical structures, but also technological innovations.  It is only possible to invest in one development at a time. Developments are built using resources and build points.  Each development requires a certain amount of each to complete, as given in the Developments chapter.  When all the total resources and build points are calculated, add these to the totals already present in the development progress box at the bottom of the Stronghold Sheet.  When progress is started on a development, there will be nothing in the boxes. When the values in the progress boxes are equal to or higher than the values needed to build the development, it is finished.  The development takes effect immediately.   Any excess amount may immediately be applied to the construction of a new development.  There is no limit to the number of developments that may be built in a season, although most developments will take at least one season of effort to complete. Besides needing resources and build points, most developments also have a prerequisite of some other development.  More details are in the Developments chapter. <h3>Espionage and Developments</h3> If an Espionage mission related to the development was successfully completed, it may have an impact on how long it takes to complete (or resources needed).  See the Developments chapter for more details. <h2>Choose Mission</h2> 
        <p1>If the mission wasn’t chosen at the end of the previous session, or in the interim, it should be chosen now. See the next chapter for all the different sorts of missions available.</p1> 
        <h2>Choose Heroes</h2> 
        <p1>The first step before going on a mission is to choose heroes. The spotlight player chooses first. Think about the suitability of the different heroes for the mission at hand. This is mostly determined by the skills of the heroes and the type of Conflict the mission uses. The list below summarizes which skills are most useful for which Conflict, although different sorts of magic (via Lore stunts) can substitute for these skills.</p1> 
        <ul>
            <l1>
                <b>Diplomacy:</b> Rapport, Society, Deceive, Empathy, Will</l1> 
            <l1>
                <b>Infiltration:</b> Stealth, Thievery, Deceive, Athletics, Fighting, Marksmanship</l1> 
            <l1>
                <b>Skirmish:</b> Fighting, Marksmanship, Athletics, Notice</l1> 
            <l1>
                <b>Warfare:</b> Tactics, Leadership, Fighting, Marksmanship</l1>
        </ul> 
        <h2>Update Skills and Consequences</h2> 
        <p1>Using the Resolve Narrative Challenge action in the narrative scenes, it is possible for players to improve skills over the course of the mission.  In addition to these advances, each player may check off one free advance for a skill that was featured in the Conflict.  It’s okay if the exact skills used aren’t remembered; as long as it’s plausible it happened.  For instance, during a Skirmish, it’s more than likely a character used Fighting or Shooting or Athletics.</p1> 
        <p1>After the free advance is taken, any skills which have three advances may be raised by one.  However, there is a restriction that every skill must have at least one skill in the rank below it.  For instance, if a character has a Superb (+5) Fighting skill that has three advances, and no other Superb skills, they may not advance it, since that would leave a Fantastic (+6) skill with no Superb (+5) skills in the rank directly below.  Essentially, this prevents advancing one skill up the ladder without take at least a few others along the way.</p1> 
        <p1>If a skill is advanced by one, erase all the advances.  Sometimes skill advances merit an additional stunt.  See the Skills and Stunts chapter for more details on how to advance skills as well as detailson stunts.</p1> 
        <h2>Refresh Fate Points and Relationships</h2> 
        <p1>Heroes are chosen by the Stronghold players prior to going on the mission, as described in the <chapref>Seasons</chapref> chapter. Each hero starts the mission with two Fate points. The spotlight player receives two additional Fate points (see the <chapref>Seasons</chapref> chapter for more on the spotlight player). Finally, each hero may refresh all of their relationship aspects, giving each one a free invoke. See the <chapref>Characters</chapref> chapter for more about relationship aspects.</p1> 
        <p1>The final activity of the season is planning what mission should be undertaken next.  Again, the spotlight player resolves any disagreements.  If this is done at the end of the evening, it helps the GM plan for next session.  It may also be useful to resolve over email or some other medium between sessions.  Play Mission The main part of a season consists of playing through the chosen mission.  This involves choosing characters, with the spotlight player resolving any disagreements, and completing the narrative phase and tactical mini-game as described in the Missions chapter. Apply Mission Results After a mission is completed, the Stronghold will possibly have attributes which are altered (the gain or loss of stability, population, resources, regions, etc.).  The details of how to resolve each type of mission are given in the <chapref>Missions</chapref> chapter.   Some of the outcomes of a mission are recorded on the Faction Sheet, such as new trade agreements, or the removal of active threats.  Also at the end of a mission, it is a good idea to write a brief note about the mission on the Chronicle sheet, including any significant consequences taken by characters or any major changes to their abilities.  This isn’t required, but having a record of when actions occurred can be useful in planning. Apply Consequences of Ignored Threats If there are any active threats from last season on the Faction sheet, the penalty for ignoring them is applied to the Stronghold now.  The penalties depend on the type of threat. Consequences of Regional Threats Regional threats make it impossible to gather resources from the region.  Thus, in the Stronghold Upkeep step, ignore that region when calculating resource totals.  Furthermore, ignoring a regional threat causes the Stronghold to some stability.  Also, ignoring a regional Threat makes it more likely the Threat will return.  See the Regions chapter for more details. Consequences of Faction Threats Most ignored faction threats cause the loss of three disposition with the faction in question.  However, if the faction threat entails military action, there are some extra steps needed to determine the consequences.  This process is detailed in the Warfare chapter. Consequences of Autarch Threats There are many different sorts of threats posed by the Autarch.  These are detailed in the Autarch chapter.  Each threat has consequences of a different nature. Calculate Build Points Finally, add the population and stability for the Stronghold and divide the result by five (rounding up).  The result is the total number of build points the Stronghold will have available for the coming year. Stronghold Upkeep The Stronghold Upkeep step entails the recovering of resources, updating stability and population due to factors such as resource availability, and the building of developments. Gather Resources The first step during upkeep is to calculate all the resources each region controlled by the Stronghold provides.  Note that any region which had an ignored threat this season will not produce resources.  Record the sum of all the resources produced (food, ore, wood, timber, mana, and luxuries) at the bottom of the Stronghold sheet.  Frequently, this tally is unchanged between seasons. Luxuries Luxuries can be traded for other goods at a 2:1 ratio. Trade Agreements Any trade agreements with other factions (from Diplomatic missions) may now be used to modify the final tally of resources.  Usually this is accomplished by trading one sort of resource for another.  Refer to the Faction Sheet for active trade agreements.  For each active trade agreement, check off the box on the Faction Sheet to mark the passing of one season.   When all the boxes are filled in, the trade agreement is over. Harvest Mana As mentioned in the Overview and Magic chapters, channelers (characters with a non-zero Channeling skill who can use magical energy) may spend time bonding with a region that has a non-zero mana resource value.   Characters with a non-zero Channeling skill who didn’t go on this season’s mission may be assigned to regions with a non-zero mana resource value in order to undertake the time consuming process of withdrawing the magical energy from the land. In any region where a channeler has been assigned for the season, the channeler is able to harvest mana, adding it to their mana pool.  However, there is an upper limit to the amount of mana that may be recovered in a region, which is equal to three times the character’s Channeling Skill.  See the Magic chapter for more details.  Make sure to note on the character’s sheet where this mana came from. Example: Catrin spent a season in The Obsidian Wood, which has a mana resource value of 3.  Catrin’s Channeling skill is 4, and she currently has 10 mana in her pool.  Normally, she would add 3 to her mana pool (since the Obsidian Wood has 3 manal), but her pool can only reach twelve, so one point is lost. Calculate Stability Stability is affected by the population and the amount of food harvested.  If there is less total food than the population, the stability of the Stronghold drops by one.  Finally, if the amount of food drops very low, less than ½ the population of the Stronghold, the stability will drop by two. Character Upkeep Characters that didn’t go on the previous mission may make progress towards removing longer term consequences.  If a character wasn’t on a mission this season, they may remove a major consequence (which takes a season to remove). If they don’t have a season consequence, they may check off one box towards removing a severe consequence.  When four boxes are checked, the severe consequence is removed.  So, it takes four seasons of rest to remove such a severe consequence. <h1>Determine New Threats</h1> Now any coming threats for the next season are determined. Rolling for Region Threats Three dice are rolled to determine if there are new threats for each region.  If all dice come up negative, the region rolled for has a threat.  It is up to the GM to choose the nature of the threat, following the guidance in the Threats section of the Regions chapter. Regions that had previously ignored threats will have aspects on them related to the threat.  In that case, one fewer dice is rolled for each such aspect (a minimum of one dice is rolled).  See the Regions chapter for more details.  Note that this is one of the few rolls which isn’t a skill roll.  No fate points or aspects may be used to alter the result. Choosing Region Threats If a Threat is present in a region, choose an appropriate Threat from the end of the Regions chapter.  Unlike the faction Threats, these usually aren’t closely related to any particular region.  Instead, the GM chooses one which fits thematically. Determine New Faction Threats Faction threats are determined differently depending on whether the faction has a lower than negative two or not.  If the faction’s disposition with the Stronghold is negative two or higher, threats are determined by rolling three fate dice, in the same fashion as for region threats. If the faction’s disposition is negative three or less, threats are not rolled for.  Instead, one threat is chosen each year. Choosing Faction Threats In the Factions chapter, there are example Threats listed for each faction.  The mini-game to use, as well as the results of success, failure, and ignoring the Threat are given.  There are also guidelines for creating new missions if necessary or desired. The faction threats are grouped into major and minor categories.  If the threat was rolled for, it is chosen from the minor list, but if the threat occurred because the faction disposition dropped low enough, it is chosen from the major list. Determine Autarch Threat There may also be a threat from the Autarch.  These threats are not determined randomly, but rather by the current year of the campaign.  As the campaign progresses and the Autarch’s current war comes to a close, these threats grow in frequency and intensity.  See the Autarch chapter for more details. Planning Next Mission The final activity of the season is planning what mission should be undertaken next.  Again, the spotlight player resolves any disagreements.  If this is done at the end of the evening, it helps the GM plan for next session.  It may also be useful to resolve over email or some other medium between sessions.</p1>
    </Story>
</Root>
