<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<Root><Table><chapter>Threats</chapter> <p1>Threats are the central source of adversity the heroes must face. There are three types of threats: regional, ally, and enemy. Regional threats are randomly determined and threaten the land the Stronghold controls, possibly altering supply and stability. Ally threats are also randomly determined. Ally threats threaten the relationships the Stronghold has with allied factions. Enemy threats are chosen by the Autarch player for those factions which have a negative disposition with the Stronghold (including threats for the Autarch). Enemy threats are chosen from a list of available options, somewhat like the missions available to the Stronghold players.</p1> <h1>Regional Threats</h1> <p1>Regional threats are checked for at the end of every season. See the <chapref>Seasons</chapref> chapter for more details. Each region is rolled for using a d20, and if a 1 is rolled, a regional threat occurs</p1> <h2>Ignoring Regional Threats</h2> <p1>If a regional threat is ignored, the region will produce no resources for that season. During Stronghold upkeep at the beginning of the season, do not add the region’s resources to the total produced. Furthermore, the Stronghold suffers 1 point of stability loss, and the region gains a permanent aspect reflecting the fallout from the ignored threat. This permanent aspect may replace a permanent aspect already on the region.</p1> <h2>Mission Success and Failure</h2> <p1>If a regional threat mission is successful, the Stronghold gains one stability. On failure, the Stronghold loses one stability (some missions have an option for no stability loss or gain). In either case, as long as the Stronghold attempts to deal with the threat, resources may be pulled from the region.</p1> <h2>Developments</h2> <p1>Some developments allow the Stronghold to ignore threats. If used on a regional threat, no stability is gained or lost. It’s as if the threat never happened.</p1> <h2>Regional Threat Table</h2> <Table xmlns:aid="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/4.0/" aid:table="table" aid:trows="12" aid:tcols="3"><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667"><b>d20 Result</b></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667"><b>Conflict</b></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667"><b>Difficulty</b></Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667">1</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667">Warfare</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667">5</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667">2-3</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667">Diplomacy</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667">4</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667">4</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667">Diplomacy</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667">5</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667">5-6</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667">Infiltration</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667">3</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667">7-8</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667">Infiltration</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667">4</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667">9</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667">Infiltration</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667">5</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667">10-11</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667">Skirmish</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667">3</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667">12-14</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667">Skirmsh</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667">4</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667">15-17</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667">Skirmish</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667">5</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667">18-19</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667">Skirmsh</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667">6</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667">20</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667">Skirmish</Cell><Cell aid:table="cell" aid:crows="1" aid:ccols="1" aid:ccolwidth="87.66666666666667">7</Cell></Table><h1>Ally Threats</h1> <p1>TBD</p1> <h2>Ally Threat Table</h2> Result	Mini-game	Difficulty -5	Warfare	5 -4	Skirmish	5 -3	Skirmish	4 -2	Diplomacy	3 -1	Diplomacy	4 0	Diplomacy	5 +1	Diplomacy	6 +2	Diplomacy	7 +3	Infiltration	3 +4	Infiltration	4 +5	Infiltration	5 <h1>Enemy Threats</h1> <p1>TBD</p1> <h1>Random Threat Listing</h1> <p1>Following are a number of examples of regional threats.  These may be used as is, or modified slightly to fit the region.  If a threat is ignored, and later the same region has another threat, it is easiest to have the threat recur, if it makes sense. For instance, the bandits who were ignored have come back for more, etc.</p1> <mission>Ogres Raid Tarrydale Farms</mission> Conflict Skirmish Difficulty 5 An unruly group of ogres are stealing food and generally causing mayhem at the Tarrydale Farms.  They’re operating out of a series of caverns a few miles away from the farms. Guarding the Grain Cart The heroes must escort a shipment of grain out of Tarrydale.  Of late, these food carts have been ambushed by ogres, so the farmers would like an escort out of the valley. •	Staying alert for signs of trouble •	Helping fix a broken wheel •	Repelling an ogre attack •	Tracking down the missing horse from the ogre attack •	Calming down Cedric the farmer Tracking the Ogres After aiding the farmers with their goods, the heroes have a better idea of where the ogres are launching their raids from.  They can follow the trail from where the ambush took place.  The tracks lead through a dense forest and into a rocky cavern. •	Follow the ogres’ footprints •	Burning nettle poisoning •	Rescuing a farmer from an ogre’s grasp •	Get past sentry •	Gnarlbone, the ogre leader, constructed a rockfall trap in the mine <h2>Skirmish: Ogre Lair</h2> The ogres aren’t particularly bright, mostly focusing on smashing the heroes up.  They don’t mind ganging up on someone who looks particularly feeble. Tactics The ogres work together to smash the heroes.  The minion ogres will work together to swarm a target, creating aspects to help improve damage.  If Gnarlbone is taken out of the fight, the other ogres will take 3 mental stress. Opponents Gnarlbone – Ogre Leader Physical	 Mental	 Consequences	-2  -4  -6  Superb (+5)	Physique, Fighting, Athletics Great (+4) 	Will  Good (+3)	Tactics Decent (+2)	Notice •	Cunning – for an Ogre •	Hamfists •	Iron capped tusks •	Shrug off Pain – Spend a fate point to add +4 on any defense using Athletics •	Smash! – Spend a fate point to add +4 on any attack roll using Fighting Ogre (1/Player) Physical	 Mental	 Consequences	-2  -4  Superb (+5)	Physique Great (+4) 	Athletics Good (+3)	Fighting Decent (+2)	Tactics, Will •	Massive club •	Dumb as a sack of bricks •	“Stop Talking – I Smash You!” •	Whirling Attack •	Shrug off Pain – Spend a fate point to add +4 on any defense using Athletics <mission>Bandits at Echo Lake</mission> Mini-game	Skirmish Ignore	No production for one season, -1 stability Failure	No production for one season Success	+1 stability A group of bandits have been stealing ore from the Echo Lake mine.  They have taken up residence in a collection of old abandoned farmhouses, which they access through an unused series of passages in the mines.  This threat works well for any region that has significant amounts of ore. Scene: Interviewing the Farmers The heroes head out to Echo Lake, with the goal of interviewing the farmers and figuring out where and how the bandits operate.  Eventually they learn that the bandits have been seen entering and exiting the mine by nightfall. •	Interviewing Erasmus, whose farm is near the mine. •	Visit Matilde, whose son is rumored to run with the bandit gang. •	Gavin, a young bandit, tracks the heroes and watches what they do. •	Help catch a missing pig. Scene: Investigating Echo Lake Mine The group looks around the mine for clues.  A series of passages which are no longer in use open out onto a field in the middle of a small valley, where the bandits have taken up residence. •	A weakened beam shows signs of giving way. •	Finding clues amongst the passages. •	Strange odor, probably from a pocket of methane gas. •	Swarm of red stinging cave beetles. Skirmish: Bandit Attack The bandits are led by The Claw, a mine worker fired for courting the mine owner’s daughter.  They have set up shop in a small complex of abandoned farmhouses.   Tactics The bandits try to use the buildings for cover, moving around to set up coordinated strikes. Opponents The Claw – Bandit Leader Physical	 Mental	 Consequences	-2  -4  -6  Superb (+5)	Notice Great (+4) 	Thievery, Marksmanship Good (+3)	Athletics, Fighting, Physique Decent (+2)	Will, Deceive Average (+1)	Nature •	Moves quieter than a deer •	Safer in the shadows •	The ore is rightfully ours •	Everyone has a price, including me •	Disfigured right hand •	Shifty movement – Move one extra zone with free movement (not for regular movement) •	Crack shot – Two extra shifts on successful ranged weapon attack Bandit (1 / Player) Physical	 Mental	 Consequences	-2  -4  Great (+4) 	Marksmanship Good (+3)	Athletics, Thievery, Fighting Decent (+2)	Notice, Will, Deceive, Physiqe Average (+1)	Nature •	We follow The Claw! •	Poor quality swords •	Shifty movement – Move one extra zone with free movement (not for regular movement) <mission>Revolt!</mission> Conflict Diplomacy Difficulty 4 The farmers and harvesters feel taken advantage of.  Must work to bring back morale.</Table></Root>
